<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The curtaine of Church-povver and authoritie in things called indifferent Drawne and laid open, to shew the many infectious sores and maladies they bring in, and cover. Together with sundry infallible reasons, proving that the service of God, and the generall good of the Church and common wealth require that they should be abolished. By Ia: Henric</title>
            <author>Henric, James.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 225 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13071</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111374</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846736</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846736</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11723</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02930)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11723)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1207:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The curtaine of Church-povver and authoritie in things called indifferent Drawne and laid open, to shew the many infectious sores and maladies they bring in, and cover. Together with sundry infallible reasons, proving that the service of God, and the generall good of the Church and common wealth require that they should be abolished. By Ia: Henric</title>
                  <author>Henric, James.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 107, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Successors of G. Thorp],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed MD C XXXII [1632]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Discipline --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11723:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11723:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CURTAINE OF CHVRCH-POVVER AND AVTHORITIE IN THINGS CALLED INDIFFERENT:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Drawne and laid open, to ſhew the many infectious ſores and maladies they bring in, and cover.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with ſundry infallible reaſons, proving that the ſervice of God, and the generall good of the Church and Common wealth require that they ſhould be aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Ia: Henric.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſai. 29.13, 14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Foraſmuch as this people draw neere me with their mouth, and with their lips doe honour me, but have removed their heart far from me, and their feare towards me is taught by the precepts of men: Therefore behold, I will proceed to doe a marvellous worke amongst this people: for the wiſedome of their wiſemen ſhall periſh, and the underſtanding of their prudent men ſhall be hid.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ier. 8.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Is there no balme in Gilead? is there no Phyſitian there? Why then is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> health of the daughter of my people recovered?</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed MDCXXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11723:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11723:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>VVEe may ſee cleerly how it oft fareth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt and the Churches, by that which he ſaid againſt the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes, when he proved that in divers particulars they had made the word of God of none effect through theire tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The Church of Rome hath in that evill exceeded them,<note place="margin">Marc. 8.6. to 14.</note> Bellarmin, in his <hi>4</hi> book of the unwritten word of God Chap. <hi>2.</hi> making three ſorts of traditions, calleth one <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> which he ſaith <hi>are introduced from ancient cuſtomes by the Prelates, or by the people, and creepingly, by the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and unqueſtioning agreement of the people, have gained as it were ſtrength of law:</hi> with ſuch are wee to deale.<note place="margin">Seſſ. 21. Chap. 1.2.</note> The Councell of Trent declareth that <hi>this power hath the Church alwayes had in miniſtring of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi> (haveing their ſubſtance) <hi>to ordaine or alter that which ſhe judged to be moſt expedient for the vtilitie of thoſe that receive them.</hi> I could wiſh the Church of England, at least in her practiſe, had never incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſuch kind of opinions and traditions. But conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how things goe there, I thought my ſelfe ſo much bound to Chriſt, my Saviour, that I muſt diſcover the miſcheivous wounds and ſoares they bring in and cover; that by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God and care of them that are ſenſible of the hurts, there may happily be found <hi>balme in Gilead to cure them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 8.22 Lame. 1.12</note> For <hi>ſtay</hi> and conſider <hi>all ye that paſſe by,</hi> If the Church of England, like the man m the Goſpel, that <hi>went downe from Ieruſalem to Iericho,</hi> be not fallen <hi>among theeues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc 10.30 31.32.</note> that have ſtripped her of her raiment &amp; wounded her; whether many Prieſts and Levits have not come downe <hi>that way,</hi> and ſeene her, and <hi>paſſe by on the other ſide.</hi> Whether I, ſeeing the wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re herein manifeſted,<note place="margin">Verſ. 37.</note> could doe leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:11723:3"/> then have compaſsion on her; whether I have not, as far as God hath enabled me, <hi>bound</hi> them vp, and powred into them the wine of his law and the <hi>oyle</hi> of the Goſpel: whether I had not reaſon to complaine of them, that have ſo cruelly hurt her: and if in ought I have donne the part of a <hi>neighbour;</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what our Lord ſaith, <hi>goe thou &amp; doe likewiſe.</hi> Be not of them <hi>that cover with a covering,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 30.1.</note> 
               <hi>but not of Gods Spirit.</hi> But rather remember Chriſts words, <hi>beware of falſe Prophets, that come to you in ſheepes clothing, but inwardly are ravening wolves: ye ſhal know them by theire fruits.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 7.15. &amp; 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>Doe men gather grapes of thornes, or figs of Thiſtles? A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit, neither can a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit.</hi> The preſbiterie and the hierarchie may bee theeſe two trees, which thou ſhalt know by theire fruits, he that ſeekes the good hath adverſaries about the bad. I may find ſuch in this worke: but he that ſhall judge both them and me is able to defend it. If then they conſtraine me to ſay with my Leader. <hi>I have laboured in vaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 49.3.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſpent my ſtrength for nought,</hi> I ſhal adde, <hi>yet ſurely my jugment is with the Lord and my worke with my God.</hi> To his grace there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and protection, I muſt commend it, and reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord: <hi>IA: HENRIC.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:11723:3"/>
            <head>THE CVRTAINE OF CHVRCH-POWER AND Authority, in things called indifferent; drawne, and <hi>laid open, to ſhew the many infectious ſoares, and</hi> maladies they bring in, and cover.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Deny not, but that the Church may make ordinances, when they be but few, eaſie, innocent, and tend onely to the keeping of that, which is in effect required, though not in termes expreſſed in Gods word.<note place="margin">Aug. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. lib. 1. c. 11.</note> In the primitive Church many put off their Baptiſme, either till age, when the heat of ſinne was well over; or till they were ſicke, and in danger of death; becauſe they had a conceit, that ſinnes after Baptiſme were greater, that in Baptiſme all ſinnes and ſtaines were waſhed away, and in the meane they might give more ſcope to their luſts: whereupon the Church made a Canon, that none might bee a Biſhop, who had beene baptized in his bed, becauſe ſuch a one ſeemed to be baptized rather of neceſſity, then faith, and love; which was a ſcandall, deſerving ſuch an ordinance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; becauſe thoſe, who are choſen to that office, ſhould be <hi>blameleſſe,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">1 Tim 3.2. Tit. 1.7.</note> It is alſo a great ſcandall to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:11723:4"/> Chriſtianity, that there are many Chriſtians, ſo called, who are common dicers, that in halfe an houre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive men, their wives, and children, of halfe, &amp; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time of their whole eſtates: a vice that is oft accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with curſing, ſwearing, fighting, killing, and ſuch fearfull concomitants:<note place="margin">Synod. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinop. 6. c 50. Concil. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib. c. 79.</note> In remedy whereof, Councels have ordained that ſuch ſhould be put from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. What Chriſtian will deny, but that there is need of ſuch an ordinance? as being in effect required, 1 <hi>Cor. 5.5.7.11.13.</hi> Other inſtances might be given of the like nature.</p>
            <p>As touching points of faith, and ſalvation, determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Councels againſt heretikes, ſuch as the Arians, Pelagians, Arminians, &amp;c. they are not ſo much to bee obſerved, becauſe the Councell hath ſo determined, as becauſe it is decreed according to Gods word, which the Councell cleereth from falſe gloſſes; that ſo the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience in ſuch caſes may not be to mens ordinances, but to the word of God,<note place="margin">Iſa. 2.4.</note> that ſhould <hi>judge amongst the nations;</hi> and no man, or company of men may <hi>ſit in the temple of God, as God,</hi> ordaining lawes, and pointes of faith binding the conſcience The decrees of that Councell Act. 15. bound not but for a time, touching abſtinence from blood,<note place="margin">See Moulin Buckler of faith. Sect. 91.</note> and things ſtrangled. And eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Councell may not thinke it ſufficient, in like caſes, to ſay as the Apoſtles might, <hi>It ſeemed good unto the Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 15.25.</note> 
               <hi>and to us.</hi> The Apoſtles had a more warrantable authority and commiſſion, then provinciall Biſhops have. The firſt Councell of Nice determined well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Arrians. They had almoſt decreed againſt Prieſts mariage; that had not beene ſo well: nor was well in ſuch Councels as after decreed it againſt her, and the word of God, which is greater: therefore the booke of Articles ſaith well, <hi>That generall Councels may
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:11723:4"/> erre, and ſometimes have erred.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Art. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The ſame Councell made the Biſhop of Rome a Patriarch, and the firſt of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs; and ſo gave him a primacy of order before the Patriarchs of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and <hi>Antioch,</hi> who had like priviledges over the other parts of the Chriſtian world; but this was not ſo well, becauſe the Beaſt aroſe to his Antichriſtian greatneſſe out of this ſea of Fathers, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and Canons, and from this ſmall beginning of preeminence. If the Church have taken on her to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine a feaſt for the bleſſed Nativity of our Saviour, and another or two in memory of his reſurrection, and the comming of the Holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Eſth. 9.21.</note> becauſe indeed the Iewes did the like in a caſe of great deliverance from the conſpiracy of proud Haman: ſhe muſt yet ſet bounds to her power, and not think ſhe may ordaine what ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dayes, ordinances, and ceremonies ſhee liſt, as the Church of Rome hath done; ordaining the feaſt of Candlemaſſe, or the purification, in place of that feaſt the Heathen kept to the Goddeſſe <hi>Febra,</hi> the mother of <hi>Mars:</hi> and ſo divers titular offices, ordinances, and Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s dayes, in place of thoſe the Heathen celebrated to their hee-Gods, and ſhee-Gods. But leaving to make any further diſcovery of her preſumptuous imitation of Iewes and Heathen in ſuch caſes; becauſe it is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet forth in a little booke called, <hi>The root of Romiſh rites,</hi> tranſlated out of French into Engliſh: let us take a little view of ſome ordinances and ceremonies recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Church of England.</p>
            <p>I deny not but the Church may ordain ſome orders for the decent worſhip of God, as touching the time and place of meeting, and reverent behaviour while the people are there; that men ſhould kneele, and be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered in the time of prayer; heare the word with ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and reverence, when it is read, or preached;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:11723:5"/> that a pulpit ſhould be erected in a place moſt conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for hearing; a fit veſſell ſet for Baptiſme, a Table, and a Cup for the Lords Supper; that people ſhould come orderly, and not confuſedly to the ſame; that collection ſhould bee made for the poore in the beſt manner that may be; that there ſhould bee an unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in the manner of adminiſtring the Sacraments, both in words, prayer, and ceremony, and that as neere as may be to the inſtitution, and in that purity and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, wherein they were left us by the Apoſtles; that ſo one may not doe theſe things after this manner, and another after that; and ſome come to ſay, I like this,<note place="margin">1 Cor 1.12</note> I that Miniſters way beſt; like thoſe, <hi>I am of Paul, I of Apollo;</hi> that the Paſtors in every province ſhall meet once a yeare, or ſo oft as need ſhall require, to reforme abuſes, if any ariſe in doctrine or government. Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of this nature are not things meerly indifferent, but convenient and neceſſary, and doe not onely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve peace and unity, but even tend to the due per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that which is commanded in the word, directly, or by conſequence, in ſuch places as that, <hi>O come let us worſhip, and bow downe, and kneele before the Lord our maker.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 95. 1 Cor. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Let all things be done decently, and in order.</hi> There may and ought to be ſuch orders and ceremonies: but all are not thus neceſſary: for the very Article confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,<note place="margin">Act. 34. Act. 20.</note> that ſome be changed and aboliſhed (which cannot be ſaid of ſuch as are thus neceſſary) and that nothing muſt be ordained againſt Gods word. There ought to be nothing that may make Religion ridiculous, or the word of none effect.</p>
            <p>In the Church of England, the Biſhops will have an infant ſigned with the ſigne of the croſſe, <hi>In token that hereafter he ſhall not be aſhamed to confeſſe the faith of Chriſt crucified, and manfully to fight under his banner, against ſin,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:11723:5"/> the world, and the devill, and to continue Christs faithfull ſouldier, and ſervant unto his lives end.</hi> Now what a mockerie is it to ſtand ſo ſtrictly on this ceremonie, when in the meane while, they will not have ſuch a one, being come to be a man, confeſſe the faith of Chriſt againſt the <hi>Arminians,</hi> nor manfully contend for the faith againſt ſuch <hi>Pelagian</hi> and popiſh opinions? and when alſo they like a Miniſter the worſe, if in the pulpit hee ſtrive to beate downe growing <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> and Poperie, in things controverted; as if they were not things revealed, matters of faith, profitable for us to know, and of great honor to God being knowne: as that election is wholie of grace, and not of foreſeene faith, and workes; that the death, and merit of Chriſt preached, are more availeable for the converſion, and ſalvation of the elect, than of others; that regeneration and converſion are of Gods grace and power, and not of the will of man: that thoſe whom God electeth, he calleth, juſtifieth, and glorifieth; ſo that they cannot fall away finally; that juſtification while wee live here, and heaven after this life, are not of our works, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, but of Chriſt, and on our part of faith in him, yea of faith alone that worketh by love, and is fruitfull in good works. That Chriſt by one oblation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath made a full ſatiſfaction for the ſins of all the elect: that he is the only mediator of interceſſion in heaven, that can heare us, know our hearts, and by whom wee may come to the Father, and the only head of his Church to ordaine lawes binding the conſcience; that his Teſtament is ſufficient in matters of ſalvation; that there is much error, and vanitie in the doctrine of Purgatorie, Images, and other points of poperie. Now I ſay it is a meere mockery to enforce Miniſters to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:11723:6"/> ſigne everie child with the ſigne of the Croſſe, in token that he ſhall confeſſe the faith of Chriſt, and manfully fight againſt ſuch ſpirituall evils, and enimies, and yet to hinder any, much more Miniſters, to confeſſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the faith of Chriſt in theſe and the like points, by diſputes, bookes, and ſermons, and to pretend, that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Gods truth in theſe points is curious, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable not only in babes, that have more need of milke, but even in divines and men of knowledge, and that in a time when Papiſts, and Arminians ſtrive ſo much to corrupt men in them.</p>
            <p>And the mockerie is ſo much the greater. Becauſe they teach all to pray: <hi>Wee give thee humble thankes that thou hast vouchſafed to call us to the knowledge of thy grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">On the feaſt of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and Iude.</note> 
               <hi>and faith in thee. Increaſe this knowledge, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme this faith in us evermore. Granting us in this world knowledge of thy truth.</hi> And touching the Apoſtles and Prophets, <hi>grant us to bee joyned together in unity of ſpirit by their doctrine.</hi> They make men pray thus, and yet are againſt the things praied for. 2 Becauſe they make every Biſhop and every Miniſter, at his ordinantion, to promiſe <note n="*" place="margin">See the or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dering of Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons.</note> 
               <hi>to be readie with all diligence to baniſh and drive away all erroneous, and ſtrange doctrines contrarie to Gods word.</hi> Marke, <hi>all</hi> without exception, which cannot be better donne, then by manifeſting the revealed truth of God in theſe points, and ſo ſtriving earneſtlie to joyne men together in the unitie of the ſpirit by the doctrine of the Apoſtles and Prophets, as is deſired in prayer. For what a mockerie is it firſt to make him thus to vow it and pray for it, and then to hinder him from keeping that vow. 3. Becauſe they forbid the defence of Gods ordinances againſt the Hierachie, and thoſe traditions thereof, which are erroneous, of the world, and cauſes of temporizing and ignorance, making men ambitious
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:11723:6"/> that ſhould rather with the <hi>Olive tree</hi> refuſe to leave their <hi>fatnes</hi> for Dominion, like their Lord who ſaieth.<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.8. Luc 12.14</note> 
               <hi>Who made thee a judge, or a divider?</hi> And what a mockerie is it, when Biſhops, that cauſe all to bee ſigned with the ſigne of the croſſe, in ſuch a token, have not beene as carefull to get our Princes, &amp; people to ſend timely, &amp; effectuall helpe, to them that fought under Chriſts ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the Palatinate, and elſewhere; but rather flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuch Courtiers, and feigned freinds, as underhand betraied them, and the common cauſe, in ſtead of an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall going out to the helpe of the Lord againſt the mightie? How much better is God pleaſed when men are more in deeds, and leſſe in ſigne of humane inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and authoririe?</p>
            <p>The article of traditions confeſſeth <hi>that all things ought to be done to edifying.</hi> But how doth this ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie edifie? Have Engliſhmen that ſtand ſo much for the Hierarchie, &amp; for this ſigne beene made by them better ſouldiers of Chriſt then other Proteſtans? or have they not rather proved worſe, and ſo ſhewed the fruits of the hierarchie and ceremonies? So ordinarie is it with God, that bleſſeth his owne ordinances, to puniſh mens inventions and preſumptions. May it not be ſaid to ſuch maiſters of ceremonies, you can ſee the faith daily oppoſed, religion corrupted, poperye and <hi>Arminianiſms</hi> increaſe, and the poore members of Chriſt to fall by the ſword, &amp; practiſes, &amp; yet in the meane be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the ſigne of the croſſe, &amp; the name of a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier without the worke? neither doing it themſelves, nor ſuffering thoſe Miniſters that would, and might have prevailed by the word: theſe things muſt be left to the only care and wiſdom of the Prelates, who are well experienced in flatterie, and can beſt ſee that nothing be donne to any purpoſe, and in the meane take it for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:11723:7"/> granted, that the Church might impoſe, and adde to baptiſme, the ſigne of the croſſe ſo ſuperſtitiouſly uſed, and abuſed by the Papiſts: that it is fit to uphold that, and all other traditions, and ceremonies of the Church (though the Article confeſſe they may be changed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diverſitie of countries, times, and mens manners) and that it is authoritie enough for the uſe of the ſame now, becauſe it was ancientlie uſed (ſo was ſalt and other Romiſh traſh) becauſe ſoone after the death of the Apoſtles, or at leaſt ſoone after the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſ. lib.</note> when divers Iewes, and heathen mocked the Chriſtians with a crucified God, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, they ſigned themſelves, to ſhew they were not aſhamed of him, when who ſees not, that if their reaſon were then good, not ſuperſtitious, yet there is not the ſame now in England. Seeing there men live not amongſt ſuch mocking Iewes, &amp; heathen, unles it bee among ſuch as ſcorne and mock them with the name of Profeſſors, Diſciples, and factious Puritains, who ſtrive againſt Arminianiſme, or the hierachie, and ceremonies. Indeed theſe are ſo much ſcorned and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, that no men in England do more truly beare the croſſe of Chriſt, for his names ſake, then they, whereas their adverſaries ſtrive by all meanes to divert all men from bearing the croſſe in this manner, and by allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and threats, to make them leave the cauſe, and temporiſe as themſelves doe; who are therein enemies of the croſſe of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.18.</note> whoſe glorie is their ſhame. For they in the meane while have only borne the croſſe in a ſigne, made with the hand, like the Papiſts; which is but a mockerie in reſpect of the other. Beſides no man ever as yet maintained, that the Apoſtles, or any in their time, uſed the croſſe in baptiſme, much leſſe in ſigne only, without the worke pretended to be ſignifed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> It will be ſaide, In ſome caſes the Biſhops ſtand for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:11723:7"/> the truth, as againſt Anabaptiſts, and other hereticks. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> So doe the Romiſh Biſhops, and Ieſuites, who likewiſe have many painfull writers, and preachers, and are not behind them in ſtirring up Princes to fortitude, temperance, holines, juſtice and other vertues; but they will ſuffer nothing againſt the tenets &amp; practiſes of their hierarchie no more will the Engliſh Biſhops, who therin are alſo ſtout ſouldiers, but that is in their owne cauſe, not in Gods. Iohn ſeeth many in white, Rev. 7. and is told,<note place="margin">Rev. 7.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe are they which come out of great tribulation, and have waſhed their roabes white in the blood of the Lambe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 6.</note> This is a garment of joy and triumph given by the merits of Chriſt, to them that have had not the ſigne and name, but the worke of a ſouldier, in confeſſing, and defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the faith, and cauſe of Chriſt againſt all oppoſers. If I ſhould ſay there may bee amongſt them ſome Engliſh Martyrs, that have ſtriven againſt Arminianiſme, or at leaſt againſt the hierarchie, and have ſuffered for it, the Biſhops could not prove the contrarie. So that it is no wonder, if men doe not now offer to diſpute with them, nor alwaies ſet their names to their bookes, ſeeing the power of the Prelates to be great, as that of the inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, very dangerous, and the Biſhops themſelves ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate and mightie in friends, that they keepe their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries bookes, and arguments from being ſeene, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, and ſo plague them, that all their oppoſers ſeeme to have loſt their labour, and doe litle other good then increaſe the number of thoſe Martyrs in white, Rev. 7.</p>
            <p>This is one of the places alleadged for the wearing of the ſurpleſſe, but here ſtill they dwell in the ſigne, they will not doe the worke of thoſe Martyrs; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are againſt ſome of them: and therefore becauſe they can not looke to weare the white roabe hereafter, they will weare and make others weare an unprofitable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:11723:8"/> ſigne of it now: though men prove it to be a rite taken from the Iewes and ancient heathen,<note place="margin">See the root of Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſh Rites</note> as other of their pontificall garments, and ceremonies are. It is a cuſtome in England to bow toward the Altar or table; but what a mockerie is this, while in the meane they have no true compaſſion on the members of Chriſt, that have ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Palatinate and elſewhere, and ſo come to lie under the Altar and crie: <hi>How long Lord holy and true?</hi> They alſo ordaine holy daies for the Saints, and one for all Saints, but what a mockerie is this, while in the meane they will not ſuffer men, to confeſſe, and defend the faith, and ordinances, left by the Saints as above ſaid? This is in effect to perſecute the Saints, and then make holie daies for them, when they are dead, like them that builded the tombes of the Prophets their fathers had killed.<note place="margin">Mat. 23.29.</note> What a mockerie is it to ordaine that none ſhall hold two benefices with cure, unles he bee at leaſt a maiſter of art?<note place="margin">Can. 41.</note> as if that degree might priviledge him to bee worſe then others.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Can. 24.</note>What a mockerie is it to ordaine <hi>that in all Cathedrall Churches the communion ſhalbe adminiſtred, uppon principall feast daies, ſometime by the Biſhop, ſometime by the Deane, and ſometime by a Canon or Prebendarie, uſing a decent cope, and being aſsiſted with the Goſpeller and Epiſteler;</hi> when none of all theſe things are ordained in the new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. That is neither Dioceſſan, or provinciall Biſhops, Deanes, Canons, Prebendaries, Epiſtlers, Goſpellers, Cathedrall Churches nor Copes; or as another Canon enjoyneth all ſorts to <hi>weare on their ſurpleſſes, hoodes ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their degrees,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. 5 8</note> 
               <hi>whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they adminiſter the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> Theſe things nouriſh pride, ambition, idlenes, nonreſidencie, temporiſing, and ignorance; Gods ordinances are not the better obſerved by them, but the worſe, as alſo by the pettie Canons, <note n="*" place="margin">See Ear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les charac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters c. 69. of ſinging men.</note> and their ſinging, while the people
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:11723:8"/> can neither joyne with them, nor underſtand them, they ſerve but for a vaine ſhew, to pleaſe ignorance, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh people.</p>
            <p>Divers Canons, courts and cuſtomes depend on the Epiſcopall office, authoritie and Miniſterie, which muſt needes be ſore burdens, becauſe that office is not <hi>ex jure divino,</hi> much leſſe the Canons, courts, and proceedings. It would wearie a man to thinke of all the abuſes in the Biſhops courtes, in ſubordinate officers, the complaints of them that are oppreſſed by them, in every dioceſſe, ſhew them to bee popiſh, and intolerable, and therefore I will paſſe by them.</p>
            <p>As touching kneeling at the Sacrament which alſo is an ordinance of humane authoritie, I know there are many in the Church of England who, perceiving that there is no quiet living there without obedience to this and the like ordinances, conſider that it is but a geſture, that the Sacrament is called the Euchariſt, which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies thankſgiving, and the cup is called the cup of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; that giving of thankes, or bleſſing of God, is a kind of prayer, and this being the Sacrament of thankſgiving may be received kneeling, eſpecially where men are not permitted to receive it otherwiſe. I anſwer that as theſe are the reaſons of ſuch as be conformable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they know not how to helpe it, I purpoſe not to diſpute againſt them. But theſe are not the reaſons of the Biſhops and ſuch others as impoſe this ceremonie of kneeling. Take the Church repreſentative, as they would have it taken for the aſſembly of Biſhops, and others in convocation, and of them that ſee their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances obſerved, &amp; there is no ſuch profeſſed doctrine or explanation of the reaſon, that becauſe it is a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of thankſgiving, and the cup a cup of bleſſing, men ought to kneele in receiving it, and if there were,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:11723:9"/> yet that is not a ſufficient reaſon for them to preſume to impoſe it, without warrant of precept or example in holy writ. For they know that all or moſt of the Pſalmes are expreſſe prayers, praiſes and thankſgivings: yet neither doe wee reade that Chriſt made men ſing them kneeling; neither doe the Biſhops, no nor the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts themſelves, make men ſay, reade, or ſing them knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. It is true that in thankſgiving, it is not only lawfull, but beſt beſeeming to doe it kneeling, that as ſoone as ever the Sacrament is received, it can not but be good to give thankes kneeling: ſo doe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, yet before and after meate men give God thanks ſtanding, yea many doe it ſitting, and the Biſhops are not troubled with it. Beſides the act of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, is not an action or praier of thankſgiving, but an act of receiving. And it is out of queſtion, that Chriſt adminiſtred this Sacrament to his Apoſtles, as all, or the moſt part of them were ſitting: Mathew ſaith, <hi>As they were eating,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 26.26.</note> 
               <hi>Ieſus tooke bread, bleſsed it, and gave it.</hi> Now no man wil be ſo mad, as to imagine that they were ſupping, or eating the Paſchal-lambe on their knees. Marke ſaith:<note place="margin">Mar. 14.18. verſ. 22.</note> 
               <hi>As they ſate and did eate, Ieſus ſaid, one of you ſhall betray me:</hi> then it followeth, <hi>And as they did eate, Ieſus tooke bread, and bleſſed, and gave it:</hi> that is, therefore as they <hi>ſate.</hi> If it had beene neceſſarie that men ſhould take it kneeling, Chriſt would have commanded them to riſe, and take it kneeling (a command that better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemes him then a Biſhop, or Miniſter) or the Apoſtles would have ſo ordained, and ordered it: Luke ſaith, <hi>when the howre was come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 22. 14. verſ. 19.</note> 
               <hi>he ſate downe, and the twelve Apostles with him:</hi> and ſo (as Mathew, and Marke adde) <hi>as they did eate he tooke bread, and gave it.</hi> As in effect Luke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf addeth, <hi>And hee tooke bread,</hi> or to ſhew that though this banquet came after ſupper, yet it was before they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:11723:9"/> were riſen: and therefore Mark ſaith, it was <hi>As they did eate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After that, the Corinthians tooke the Sacrament as they were eating or ſupping, wherefore the Apoſtle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth them ſaying, <hi>In eating everie one takes his owne ſupper before, and one is hungrie, and another drunken,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.21.</note> 
               <hi>what have yee not houſes to eate, and drinke in?</hi> He would not have them come to Church to ſatiſfye hunger; he doth not reprove the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſitting at the Lords ſupper, but for making a meale before it, and together with it: which was a reaſon, why the time was changed, and appointed to be before men goe home to dinner. <hi>If any man hunger let him eate at home:</hi> then he addeth,<note place="margin">Verſ. 34.</note> 
               <hi>and the rest I will ſet in order when I come:</hi> that is, other matters, this is already ordered: whence it appeares, that in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time, it was received ſitting or ſtanding, as a ſupper is received and uſually eaten. And verie reaſon doth manifeſt that this order could not ſodainly be changed but by degrees, and as ſuperſtition, errour, &amp; ignorance increaſed. Chriſt, that inſtituted this Sacrament, did it to confirme and ſtrengthen our faith, and to make us <hi>ſhew the Lords death,</hi> &amp; the benefit thereof to our owne ſoules, and others. This is beſt performed by medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that as the bread is broken for us, and given to us, ſo was Chriſt, that as it feedes, and ſaves our bodies from periſhing; ſo doth Chriſt our ſoules; that as his promiſe is to ſave all that beleeve in him, receive, and feed on thoſe promiſes, ſo he ordained this Sacrament as a ſigne, and ſeale of the ſame to every true beleever, to whom in particular it is given, and applied. His new covenant is to <note n="*" place="margin">Iet. 31.33</note> 
               <hi>write his law in our hearts,</hi> that wee may, by vertue of that covenant in his blood, walke in his waies; and for what is paſt to <hi>remember our ſins no more:</hi> and each man takes the Sacrament as an aſſurance
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:11723:10"/> thereof, to his owne ſoule, that groanes under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of them. The Sacrament is beſt received, when wee mind and beleeve theſe, and the like things, and hunger and thirſt for them: therefore there is no more need of kneeling in the act of receiving, then in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſame offered in the word preached; nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſo much Praier on our knees is neceſſarie before receiving that wee may bee prepared, and receive ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinglie; and after receiving to ſhew all humble thankfulnes: but in giveing us this Sacrament, at his table, the Lord would ſhew us a great favour, as a great Lord or Prince, doth to a poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when he calls him to his table: he requires him not to come, &amp; eate knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: for that is not an action fitting the intended fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, nor the act of eating a ſupper. It is the beſt part of manners to be ordered by him, as the gueſts were that were firſt ſet. In ſtanding, or ſitting he may behave himſelf reverently, as they doe that ſo receive in the reformed Churches.</p>
            <p>If any do yet replie, it is better for men to command kneeling in receiving the Sacrament, though the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and others in their time, received it ſitting; that is to infer, that the like may be commanded, that the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſhall kneele while a child is baptiſed, or ſprinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled that the Kings, &amp; Preiſts of Iſrael might have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the like; as moſt neceſſary in circumciſion, and in eating the Paſchal-lambe, that is, that all ſhould eate it kneeling: for the eating of the Lambe before Chriſts death, was in place of this Sacrament: but this they could not doe: for God ſaith of the Paſſeover: <hi>according to all the rites of it and according to all the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies thereof,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num 9.3.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall yee keepe it.</hi> Not with others, much leſſe with contrarie. It may be, that the ſtriking of the doore poſts with blood, was not after ſo neceſſary; nor
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11723:10"/> perhaps, the eating of it in haſt, and with ſtaves in their hands; becauſe the Angel had then paſt their houſes, and the journey into Canaan was paſt: but the reſt of the ceremonies mentioned, verſ. 12. were to remaine.<note place="margin">Verſ. 12.</note> No man might preſume to change them. No more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed may any do theſe, ſave in ſuch as doe not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily belong to the receiving of the Sacrament, as that there ſhould be a Paſchal-lambe eaten at the ſame time, that it ſhould be at a ſupper time, when men make a meale, and not rather before dinner: the Apoſtle chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged one, that it ſhould not be eaten when men eate a meale, or for hunger, and the other was changed upon the ſame, or like reaſon. But this of the geſture can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo well be changed, much leſſe to one ſo contrary, as that of kneeling. The example of Chriſt, and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles have the force of a precept, that it ſhould be eaten afer the manner of a ſupper; and the greateſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference and contrarietie of geſture that can be in ſuch an action, is that betweene ſitting and kneeling, which of all others is fartheſt from that uſed in the inſtitution and time of the Apoſtles; and therefore muſt needes be diſpleaſing to God, the rather becauſe it hath beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, impoſed, and practiſed by idolatrous Papiſts.</p>
            <p>It is the neceſſitie of conformitie impoſed upon Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters that furniſheth them with arguments to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie. You will ſay, many in the primitive Church received it ſtanding. This cannot properly be called a change, becauſe men do oft eate ſtanding; and it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that when Chriſt, &amp; after his aſcenſion the Apoſtles, gave the bread, ſome might receive it ſtanding. Beſides the conveniencie pleades for the geſture. For when as in Diepe, and Paris, and ſome other Churches of France, there be about 4000 to communicate at a time, thirtie or fortie of them come one behind an other toward the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:11723:11"/> ſide of the table, where the firſt three or fower, ſtanding ſtill, receive, and then paſſing forward give way to the next three, till all bee ſerved; whereas if all ſhould ſit, and riſe by companies, it would aſke a far longer time. Beſides, this is a reverent geſture, and a lawfull, and an indifferent meane betweene ſitting, and kneeling. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Some anſwer, there cannot bee too much reverence in ſuch an action, therefore kneeling is beſt. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> The ſame reaſon holds as well for the Sacrament of baptiſme, and the word preached, that witneſſes, who anſwer for a child ſhould kneele when it is ſprinkled; that men of age, baptiſed in the primative ages, ſhould have kneeled while they were ſprinckled or dipped; that all ſhould kneele al the while the word is preached, becauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God ſpeakes unto us, and plainely manifeſts his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall wiſdome, power, and grace; whereas in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thoſe things are only taught us by ſigne, and ſeales.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> It is objected, that they are commonly prentiſes, and people of the leaſt knowledge, who refuſe to kneele.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Anſw. Many that had as little knowledge, and could as ill give a reaſon of their faith, were Martyrs in Queene Maries daies. Howſoever they have leſſe knowledge in this point, though they be Biſhops and Doctors who mayntaine that kneeling may be impoſed, as moſt fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in this action.<note place="margin">Pleſſis my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of iniquitie, progreſſ. 50.51.</note> For it was Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> the third that firſt ordained kneeling at the Sacrament, about the yeare 1220 when a little before the doctrine of tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, determined in the Councell of Lateran, in the time of his predeceſſor <hi>Innocent</hi> the third: and then in the yeare 1264, that feaſt was ordained by <hi>Vrban</hi> the fourth,<note place="margin">Platin in vit. Honor. 3. Annot.</note> which Papiſts call Gods daie, or <hi>Corpus Chriſti,</hi> with them the greateſt in the yeare, when withall pompe, and ceremonie the bread is caried in proceſſion
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:11723:11"/> and adored of all. Thence it followed that men ought to kneele before it. And that this ceremonie was held neceſſarie, as alſo bowing to the Altar: both which might bee uſed by ſome, in an ignorant, and officious devotion, before the time of <hi>Honorius,</hi> but ratified, and received, by all the Weſterne Churches, it could not bee, till the Pope had power, and champions to maintaine it. Theſe were the locuſts, the Regulars. <hi>Innocent</hi> the third confirmed the order of Friars, whoſe head was <hi>Francis,</hi> ſo famous for lying wonders; and <hi>Honorius</hi> the third, that of the preachers, whoſe head was <hi>Dominick,</hi> canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed for a ſaint by the following Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the 9, theſe ſtouly maintained the cauſe againſt the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> and <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> whileſt theſe popes were buſie in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Kings to conquer <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and perſecuting the Emperours, <hi>King Iohn</hi> of England, and other Princes. Such was the religion of thoſe times, &amp; the ages next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; for as one obſerves, <hi>If the Biſhops of Rome ſent into any countrie, it was not principally to preath the Goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pleſſis my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie. prog. 24.</note> 
               <hi>but to broach their owne ceremonies, their ſingings, their ſervice in latine, howres, organs, Altars, tapers, &amp;c. ſtirring up Princes to enforce their ſubjects to uſe and practiſe them, who would faine have kept themſelves to the firſt inſtitution of the Church, in the puritie of the Goſpel.</hi> And as he obſerveth, <hi>the worſer ſort of men are most zealous in ſuch things to ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and obſcure their evill acts,</hi> and indeed to ſerve them in ſteade of the Religion which Chriſt ordained: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though they neglected and contemned found doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, true faith, knowledge, zeale, and the like graces, yet they would build ſtately <hi>Temples,</hi> bow to the Altar and to the bread, which is called the body of Chriſt, and thinke they did God the better ſervice.</p>
            <p>I will not ſay that thoſe Engliſh Biſhops, and Doctors, who had hand in the reformation, and ordained knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:11723:12"/> at the receiving of the bread and wine, did beleeve tranſubſtantiation, or conſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or teach men to doe honour to thoſe eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, becauſe they are called the body, and blood ſacramentally: it may be it was rather to draw Papiſts the ſooner to Church, that this, and other Romiſh rites were retained; as alſo becauſe this had beene ſo long uſed, in all the world, they thought it too much as once to fall from kneeling, to ſitting, thinking that if they ſhould, ignorant Papiſts, of which the land was then peopled, would never bee drawen to Church, or to hearken to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in other things, when having once laid theſe things for Rules, like the Lutherans in their tenets, they can heare nothing to the contrarie, but above all, becauſe they knew the office of a Dioceſſan Biſhop, could not ſubſiſt, in theſe daies of reformation, without maintaining them againſt all oppoſers of tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and humane inventions. I know that as yet there is no publick conſtitution, teaching plainly that reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ought to be done to the Elements, becauſe they are called the body, and blood of Chriſt: but if they that ſtand ſo much for kneeling at the Sacrament have not ſome ſuch ſuperſtition in it, why doe they bow toward the Altar or table, rather then toward the pulpit, or ſome other ſide of the Church, ſeeing God is every where, and on all ſides of us? And why elſe doe they begin to erect Altars, at the eaſt end of the quier in Churches, where there have beene none ſince poperie was aboliſhed? Theſe Popiſh ceremonies ſhould alſo have beene abandoned, to ſhew plainly, that they doe not favour ſuperſtition, and the worſhip of bread.</p>
            <p>They vainly ſay it argues too much boldnes, to ſit or ſtand at the table of the Lord: for it is a far greater pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, to uſe, and ordaine a ceremonie, ſo contrarie to the inſtitution, and practiſe of the Church in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:11723:12"/> Apoſtles time. The greateſt reverence wee can doe to God, is to ſtick cloſe to his ordinances, to obey and love them; and the greateſt preſumption to thinke any thing can be better deviſed, performed, and practiſed then it was in his inſtitution, with the Papiſts they doe but mock God with a name of greater reverence, whileſt they withſtand that of the inſtitution, and command another geſture, that is fartheſt from it. <hi>God is a ſpirit, and they that worſhip him, must worſhip him in ſpirit and truth:</hi> In beleeving and following his word, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, as Paul <hi>worſhipped the God of his fathers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 4. Act. 24.14. 1. Cor. 11.</note> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered this ordinance, ſo as he received <hi>it of the Lord:</hi> and not as they did whoſe feare toward God was taught by the precepts of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they worſhipped him in vaine, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards not their kneeling. It is not enough for preachers to ſay wee preach, and urge them, becauſe our Princes, and Biſhops have commaunded them, for he will anſwer <hi>Who required theſe things at your hands?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which doe but open a gap for Kings, and Prelates to commaund what they liſt. Hence came that <note n="*" place="margin">Beſides that about the Saboath</note> order of King <hi>Iames,</hi> that men ſhould not in pulpits confute poperie in things controverted, but leave that to the Biſhops, and Deanes: and that which ſucceded, that Miniſters ſhould not in the Vniverſities, pulpits and print, diſpute, preach, or write againſt <hi>Arminianiſme:</hi> they that perſwade a King, that he may doe this, ſtrive in effect to make a Pope of him. And laſtly thence comes the great do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering, and ſtrange injunctions of prelates in their viſitations, that none muſt dare to ſpeake againſt any of their orders or ceremonies whatſoever, unles he long to be ſilenced, &amp; reckoned a mad fellow:<note place="margin">Dr. Clewit at the Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, viſit. An. 1631.</note> thence comes the extreame flatterie of their Agents and Chaplaines who begin to preach thus, <hi>Auctoritàs praecipientis, est ratio prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepti,</hi> and no man conſiders that thus the Church of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:11723:13"/> Rome grew to an unlimited, and licentious power; that ſuch are the naturall fruits of the hierarchie, and they muſt needes grow worſe, and worſe.</p>
            <p>In thoſe reformed Churches where men ſit, they come to the table more prepared, with more knowledge, feare,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.20.</note> reverence, and circumſpection then ſuch men: they dare not admit a notorious drunkard, Adulterer, Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, or the like, nor any perſon utterly unknowne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it tendeth to corruption,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.6</note> 
               <hi>For a litle leaven, leave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the whole lumpe:</hi> Whereas in England all that will may come bodly: even in the Cathedrall Church in London. They that receive are utterly unknowne to them that adminiſter: no man examines them, nor teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth for them, they may be <hi>Arminians,</hi> excommunicate, prophane, or Church-papiſts, for ought that any man there knowes: they looke after no religion but this, that he kneele at the Sacrament; which if he doe but obſerve, be his life, or religion what it will, he may come boldly.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all theſe things, many ſay, ſo long as the Goſpel may be, and is freely preached, why ſhould wee trouble a Church, or leave it, our places, and meanes for ſuch faults and ordinances? Marke how God hath ſuffered theſe men to be puniſhed, and decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: the Goſpel is there freely preached, by them that will needs preach ſo; but not by the care of the Biſhops, nor yet in all points, much leſſe in all places; Miniſters are called upon to urge theſe ordinances of men, yet in the meane, they are not ſuffered to preach Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the Elderſhip, nor yet againſt <hi>Arminianiſme.</hi> It is true, that after the prohibition, the Parliament imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſucceeding, many couragiouſly preached againſt <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> and ſo doe ſome to this day: but not in the Court, nor in the Vniverſitie, much leſſe before the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:11723:13"/> Biſhops, who are ſtill againſt ſuch and have troubled many in the univerſities, and elſewhere. Neither can they reſt heere: the fruite of the <hi>Hierarchie,</hi> that is not a tree of Gods planting, muſt needes grow worſe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.2.</note> and worſe: which ſhewes it concernes the faith it ſelf to have the hierarchie aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>All which things conſidered doe manifeſt, that their pretended devotion in commanding to kneele at the Sacrament, is but like that of ſigning children with the ſigne of the Croſſe, wherein they ſtraine at a gnat and ſwallow a Camel, God muſt needes regard their knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling verie litle (as that of the Papiſts, who exceede in that, and all other humble, and devout geſtures) becauſe they are not better, or more obedient Chriſtians, they doe not more feare God, nor indeed ſo much as Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, that kneele not when they receive. For they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine that men ſhould bow the knee, ſo oft as they heare the name Ieſus mentioned in the Church, which they doe not at any other name of God, nor when Ruffins ſweare by it, as alſo that all ſhould kneele at the Sacrament. But what a mockerie is this, while in the meane, with the Papiſts, they themſelves neither bow to the word, and ordinances of God, nor conſequently to Chriſt Ieſus who is the word, nor ſuffer others that would, in ſuch proofes of Scripture, as prove that there ought to be <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 14.23. Acts. 20.17.28. Tit. 1.5. 1 Pet. 5.</note> Elders in every flock to govern the ſame, and no ſuch Lords of Gods heritage, as <hi>Dioceſſan Biſhops:</hi> no ſuch edicts againſt confutation of <hi>Arminians,</hi> nor no ſuch traditions, canons, ſet faſts as make the word of none effect. It is true that the Lent faſt is very ancient: but ſo is the myſterie of iniquitie, the Popes uſurped primacie, &amp; dominion, and many other parts of Romiſh ſuperſtition, and errour: that Engliſh Biſhops doe not yet affirme plainly, that it ought to be obſerved, as an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:11723:14"/> of God, or <hi>pari pietatis affectu, ac reverentiae,</hi> becauſe it is an ordinance of the Church: but they ſo hover about it, that men feare it will come to that, if their dominion ſtand.</p>
            <p>As to this reaſon that Chriſt faſted fortie dayes; they might as well tel us, becauſe he walked on the water, or ſuffered for ſinners: ſo therefore ſhould wee. And what a mockerie is it to make this time of the yeare, the time of repentance and mortification, when that is not to be put off till Lent, but is due at all times of the yeare, as mens ſoules, by reaſon of daylie ſins, doe oft ſtand in need of bodily faſting, and humiliation, the better to fit them for praier? Or if it were neceſſarie, what a mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is it to ordaine abſtinence from all fleſh, when men have libertie to eate the daintieſt fiſh, and other delicates uſed in fiſh dinners, banquets, and feaſts, and that as much, and as oft as they lift? And if the Prelates themſelves did not uſe it, they would not be ſo fat and luſtie as they are.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>B. Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor.</p>
                  <p>March. 4. 1631.</p>
               </note> They make great feaſts at their conſecration in Lent.</p>
            <p>But, ſay they, it makes much for the increaſe of cattel, that the ſubject may have them in more plentie, and better cheape. I could ſay, this might be much better effected by forbidding many great, and ſuperfluous feaſts as was partly practiſed in that dearth 1630; but I anſwer, They might as well tell us, that the great feaſts uſed in the twelve daies, and at other feſtivall times cauſe plenty, and cheapnes, as Lent, which coſts men more in fiſh. For who ſees not that both the one, and the other make all things the dearer? That when they approach all men ſtriving to ſtore their houſes with fleſh and fiſh, the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets are raiſed to that extremitie, that mens purſes find a dearth in the midſt of plentie. Butchers and Poulterers pay deere for their licences, which makes all extreame
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:11723:14"/> deere to ſuch poore, and ſick, or weake perſons, as muſt needs eate ſome fleſh: and Lent ended, people buy, as if they had never eaten fleſh before, which makes it want for no price. Beſides, how many thouſands are there, who are not ſick, and yet of ſuch weake conſtitutions, that they cannot live ſix weekes without eating ſome fleſh? all theſe muſt needes abſtaine to their hurt, or bee reckoned <hi>Rebels,</hi> and vexed by promoters, reſembling them of the Inquiſition.</p>
            <p>But fiſhing and ſhipping would otherwiſe decay. This were ſomewhat if they had beene, or were like to be, uſed in the defence of <hi>Religion,</hi> or againſt the enimies thereof, and not againſt ſuch as the <hi>Rochellers,</hi> but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, if men were free to eate fiſh, when they liſt, they would deſire it more, as experience ſhewes in other countries, where ſuch freedome is. Or if there were but one or two daies in a weeke, as wedneſday, ſaterday or both, wherein it were prohibited to all under great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, ſick perſons excepted, and eſpeciallie to Inhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Alehouſes, Vintners, Cookes, and Victuallers, that none ſhould dreſſe, or ſell dreſſed any fleſh, on that day, on paine of having his houſe ſhut up, and paying ſome great fine, all thorow-fare, and market townes, would ſtrive to be furniſhed with fiſh for thoſe daies and there would be more fiſhing, and fiſh ſpent in the land, in one yeare, then now there is in two; and this being only a common law and but for a day or two in a weeke, and not impoſed as a faſt, would be no burthen.</p>
            <p>But the lawes are alleadged, for this Lent faſt, as for the dominion of the Prelates, and obſervation of other their traditions, and ceremonies. I might anſwer that the way to have lawes obſerved, is to commaund things reaſonable and agreeable to Gods word, &amp; ſuch as may without hurt be obſerved: things burthenſome to little
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:11723:15"/> purpoſe, are as little regarded: That Miniſters of the Goſpel ſhould rather alleadge the law of Chriſt, that faſts, and almes, ought to be voluntarie, or obtained by the word preached, for private humiliation; or publick, being commanded by authoritie, when there is a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick calamitie, or ſome great enterpriſe in hand, nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſuch humiliation to obtaine the aſſiſtance of God; and thus only are they uſed in the reformed Churches; but in this and the like caſes, there is an example noted in a hyſtorie worthy our obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Quarrels of Paul. 5. lib. 1. p. 9.</note>The ſtate of Luca, finding many Citizens had chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their Religion and retired into proteſtant countries, publiſhed an Edict, forbidding all their ſubjects to have commerce with ſuch perſons: <hi>The Pope,</hi> that could not diſlike their intent, <hi>ſaide, The Republick had no authoritie to make ſuch an ordinance, which touched Religion, for as much as the laicques have not any power to decree in matters of Religion, although the law be in favour thereof, therefore he commanded it to be raced out of their Records.</hi> If the Pope ſaid this of States, and lawes helping and maintaining his Religion; how much more may God ſay it of Dioceſſan Biſhops, Councels, States, and all ſuch their lawes, Canons, and Edicts, as helpe the dominion of Antichriſt; nouriſh ſuperſtition, errour, and ignorance, are againſt Chriſts Kingdome, and ordinances, or in any particular make the word of none effect? whence it muſt needes follow, that becauſe they, like the Church of Rome,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.10.</note> received not the love of the truth in theſe things, therefore God muſt needes give them over to beleeve lies in other points: and becauſe in theſe things their feare toward God is taught by the traditions of men; therefore the wiſdome of their wiſemen muſt needes decay,<note place="margin">Iſa. 29.13. Mat. 15.8.</note> and periſh. A proofe whereof wee have ſeene in the Appealer now B. of Chicheſter, Dr. Iackſon
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:11723:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> and others juſtified in their errours, by the reward they obtayned for them: as alſo in their approved friend the Biſhop of London, who, beſides the erecting of Altars and Images, hath not ſhamed to urge the Edict, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to write, diſpute, or preach againſt the <hi>Arminians.</hi> And to put Mr. Davis by the lecture at Chriſts Church, becauſe he would not ſubſcribe to this, <hi>that in baptiſme orginall ſin is wholie taken away in all Infants baptiſed:</hi> Which is as much as to ſay, that the Sacraments confer grace <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> &amp; to overthrow all that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſay of Gods eternall election of ſome, and leaving of others. It is true that when the pariſh beſought the Biſhop, to admit Mr. Davis; anſwer was made, he had not ſatiſfyed his poſer in that point of baptiſme; where one may ſee, that whereas ſome ſay, there muſt bee Biſhops to trie ſuch as would be admitted to cures; or lectures; this is but a mockerie, the Biſhops ſtand like great Andirens in a chimney, which only ſerve for pompe, and ſhew, all the burthen lies on the creepers their Chaplaines: which worke might be better, and more uncorruptly performed by three or fower learned Miniſters, dwelling neere the pariſh, and being ſuch as doe the worke of Chriſt in their owne charges.</p>
            <p>For though the Biſhops have not yet put that to every one which was put to Mr. Davis; certainly if their <hi>Hierarchie</hi> ſtand, the power therof muſt needes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, till they force all to ſubſcribe to theſe, or worſe things, or ſuffer themſelves to bee ſilenced. And how prone divines are to follow, and flatter them, is manifeſt in this B. of London, who being in high favour, mighty, and able to reward whom he liſt, is flattered and humou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red like a Pope by the Biſhops, Prelates, and Preachers. And becauſe he is in ſuch honour, and authoritie; therefore it is held great preſumption to taſke, or que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:11723:16"/> any thing he doth: the <hi>Prelates</hi> that are beſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected dare not, leſt they ſhould be counted captious, envious and factious puritanes: ordinary Miniſters are over-awed by his power. And yet becauſe ſome have adventured it, he ſhamed not openly to complaine of them to the <hi>King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Feb. 15. 1631. Ier. 6.16.</note> in his laſt ſermon on that text of Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, <hi>Stand ye in the waies, and ſee,</hi> &amp;c. And firſt to infer that the Lent faſt may be called the old and good way: that yet manie are ſo bold as to ſay, <hi>wee wil not walk in it.</hi> That diſobedience to God is commonly accompanied with diſobedience to the King; and diſobedience to the King, with diſobedience to God, which is true, but not as he meant it, that they that doe not obey the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates in ſuch things are diſobedient to God, and the King. For if Prelates bind heavie burthens on men, and ſtrive to make them ſubſcribe to errour, <hi>whether it be right in the ſight of God to hearken unto them more then unto God judge ye.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.19.</note> Againe he inferred from his text, that if Kings doe not defend the Church, God juſtly ſuffers the people to diſobey them: which is true, if you take it of ſuch Church Governours, and ordinances as Chriſt ordained; but not as the Biſhop meant it, of Engliſh Biſhops, and their power, conſtitutious, Rites, and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, as if he, and a few ſuch Prelates as himſelf, were the Church of Chriſt, making it a great greivance, that any ſuffered to write, or preach againſt their practiſes (which is the only hell they ſeeme to feare) or to have the benefit of a prohibition, when they are plagued for it in the High Commiſſion, where in though he did not plainely threaten the King, yet his ſpeech glanced that way.</p>
            <p>It is true, that he ſaid much for the authoritie of Kings, obedience to them, and againſt the diſobedience of ſubjects, which doctrine he preſſed not againſt the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:11723:16"/> Papiſts, whom he ſcarce named in his ſermon, ſo far is he from the old way of Proteſtant preaching; but againſt ſuch as he eſteemes puritans, and in ſuch caſes, as were agitated the laſt Parliament; alſo in prohibitions forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the convincing of the prelacie, or their govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, traditions, and ceremonies, <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> or any other points of revived <hi>Pelagianiſme,</hi> or poperie, &amp; as an enemie of calling Parliaments, &amp; of other proceedings in ſuch caſes. That he ſaid that this was a fit ſubject for the court: for there never was diſobedience abroad, but there was a <hi>Court conventicle</hi> at home, which was the head, or cauſe of it, ſtriking at them. Who as he ſaid, as well in State policie, as in matter of Religion, find out new waies, and will not walke in the old, and good pathes: which was not ſo true of them, againſt whom he intended it, as of his boſome freind the late <hi>Duke,</hi> of <hi>Buc:</hi> or of himſelf and his faction, as the ſequell wil ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt: and namely, that they have traduced, and wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the moſt honeſt counſailes, and indeavours of the moſt noble Counſellours and wiſeſt Parliaments, under pretences of maintaining the prerogative, a trick that they have rather learned of <hi>Davus</hi> in the Comedie, then of Chriſt in the Goſpel, or if of any in the Scriptures, then of proud <hi>Haman,</hi> who, for his hate to <hi>Mordecai,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſth. 3.6.8.</note> ſaid unto the King touching the Iewes, <hi>It is not for the Kings profit to ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> or of the high Preiſts, Scribes, and Phariſes, who with praevaricating devices would prove Chriſt, and his Diſciples, that convinced them of errour, and malice to bee enemies of Caeſar, and ſuch as forbad tribute.</p>
            <p>In the primitive Church, when Chriſtians talked of the Kingdom of Chriſt and the comming thereof in the free power, and uſe of the Goſpel, and ordinances of Chriſt, their enemies perſwaded the Emperours, that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:11723:17"/> this doctrine endangered the Imperiall government, the taking of the Empire from him, and was againſt his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative. So when any talke of the reſtoring of Chriſts Kingdome, and ordinances in the government of Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiall <note n="*" place="margin">Or El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</note> Biſhops, and of the aboliſhing of Dioceſſan and Provinciall Biſhops, and their unprofitable traditions and ceremonies; the Engliſh Prelates ſay, this endangers the Regall authority, and is againſt the Kings preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and government; yea that is to refuſe the <hi>old paths,</hi> the good way of God, and their King, and impudently ſay, <hi>non ambulabimus in ea,</hi> wee will not walke in it; as the Biſhop inferred on that text, Which indeed may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be ſaid of the Biſhops themſelves, and their defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; for though one prove never ſo plainly, that the government of <hi>Dioceſsan Biſhops,</hi> though as old as the pretended <hi>primacy</hi> and uſurpations of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> is but a new way, and very pernicious to the kingdome, and people of Chriſt, and to the honour, peace, and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that King and kingdome that maintaines it; and further that the government by the common counſell of the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Act. 6.5. Cha. 15.22 Cha. 20.17 28.</p>
                  <p>1 Cor. 5 4. Tit. 1.5. Iude 3.</p>
               </note> Presbyters, and voices of the brethren, members of the congregation, is the old, and good way of God, beſt for his Church and ſervice; and likewiſe that the convincing of Pelagianiſme and Popery, defending of the truth, contending earneſtly for the faith, that was once delivered to the Saints, and walking in the light thereof, are the old paths, the good way, bee they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved never ſo old, never ſo good, the Prelates and their pertakers, doe but geere and ſcoffe at them, and further are ſo impudent as to ſay, <hi>non ambulabimus in ea,</hi> we will not walk in it. Their manifeſt hating &amp; perſecuting ſuch as ſhew them theſe old paths, this good way doe ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently prove it. Iudge then, Chriſtian Reader, if the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop have not abuſed his <note n="*" place="margin">Ier. 6.16</note> text, and that Princely and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:11723:17"/> moſt honoured audience? Is ſuch a man fit to governe and order one of thoſe two fountaines of learning, and nurſeries of Divines, the Vniverſity wherof he is Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celour, and moſt of the affaires of Religion in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties dominions, as a Pope of thoſe Kingdomes? or to be the ſpirituall guide of Princes, and Councellors, who onely beſides the Biſhops, beare all the ſway in matters of Religion? How is it poſſible that they ſhould be well informed by ſuch Prelates, or their partakers? And yet God knowes, and we ſee it plainly, they will heare no others: no not though it be manifeſtly proved, that the Prelates are as deafe and obſtinate in theſe points, as the Pope, Cardinals, and Ieſuites are in theſe points, and in others. Neither let any man thinke it ſtrange, that theſe ſhall be compared to them of the Church of Rome. For the Biſhop of Rome, and his Clarkes, that are now cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt in the ſuperlative degree, were not ſo bad in the dayes of the firſt Chriſtian Emperours: but beginning then to make the word of God of none effect by their traditions, power, and ceremonies, they grew worſe and worſe: and ſo have our Engliſh Biſhops, who follow them apace. See an inſtance in the worſt ſort of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</p>
            <p>The Ieſuites being baniſhed for their practices out of the State of Venice at Padua,<note place="margin">Quarrels of Paul. 5. lib. 2. p. 94</note> were found many copies of a certaine writing of 18. Rules, under this title, <hi>Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae aliquot ſervandae, ut cum orthodoxa Eccleſia verè ſentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Certaine rules to be obſerved, that with the orthodoxall Church we may judge, or hold aright.</hi> In the third it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that men ſhould beleeve the Hierarchical Church, although it tell us that that is blacke, which our eye jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to bee white. Would not the Biſhops have us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the Hierarchicall Church of England, when it ſaith of the Presbyterall government, that it is blacke,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:11723:18"/> which our eye judgeth to be white? And of the other ſide, of their owne dominion, and traditions, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary unto Chriſts, that they are white, which our eyes ſee to be black? In the ſeventeenth, <hi>there is a preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to take heed how men preſs or inculcate too much the grace of God.</hi> Doe not the Arminian Prelates teach us the ſame leſſon? Biſhops were not ſo corrupt, or blinde, in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes; they had not this art: but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their office and authority hath no root in Chriſt, the Truth, it is not of God, but of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they cannot but grow worſe and worſe. They that thinke it ſtrange that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Biſhops ſhould be Ieſuited, muſt yet confeſſe, that it hath beene affirmed of the late Duke of Buck: and ſome others of their abettors, ſupporters, and confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates. Howſoever we may ſee, that theſe and the like, are the fruits of maintaining their government, ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and traditions, againſt the light of Gods truth. All theſe, and divers other corruptions in religion, and miſchiefes in the State, are crept in, and covered under <hi>the Curtaine of Church power,</hi> in matter of order, decency, and things indifferent: And if they be ſtill maintained, greater abominations muſt needs follow: things cannot but grow worſe and worſe, both in Clergy and people: ignorance and errour muſt needs be thereby more and more ingendred and propagated.</p>
            <p>For they ſee well enough, that many are ſo obſervant of theſe traditions and ceremonies, that they dwell in them, they ſerve them for an entire Religion, or a cloak of one, and of mocking, and perſecuting of profeſſors: they have little or none beſides; no love to the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and hearing of Gods moſt holy word, wherby faith, knowledge, repentance, humility, and other graces are wrought in the ſoule; but like many ſimple, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant women, that will needs weare kerchers at their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:11723:18"/> churching, and yet in the afternoone, or ſoone after, run to playes and alehouſes: they are very obſervant of ſuch ordinances, and yet ſeldome come to a Sermon, and ſcarce once a yeare to the Communion. And theſe and others are not ordinances, and ceremonies ſo innocent, indifferent, and profitable, as ſome would make them. Yea therefore it is but a meere mockery and deluſion, to ſay, that though they be in themſelves indifferent, yet being commanded by authority, they become neceſſary; and men ought to be conformable, not onely that they may hold their Miniſtery, and doe good in it, but even for conſcience ſake. For 1. the Article ſaith, <hi>They may be changed according to times, and mens manners;</hi> but the times, and mens manners, who now make a religion of them, and a cloake of perſecution, do require that they ſhould be changed and aboliſhed, therefore they ought to bee changed and aboliſhed. 2. What a gappe doe they hereby open for authority to impoſe what it liſt, and to have it received by the ſame argument, though ſuperſtitious, and hurtfull to the kingdome, in the free power of the word preached? which is to abuſe Princes and Synods, and to infer they may impoſe, maintaine, and increaſe ordinances and ceremonies, that thus make the word of none effect. For grant that they may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe theſe, and it followes, they may impoſe others as hurtfull. Yet ſome are not aſhamed to preach and write much in the defence of them:<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.8 2 Cor. 4.</note> but this is <hi>after the tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men, after the rudiments of this world, and not after Christ,</hi> to corrupt the earth, and preach themſelves, not the Goſpell; when they ſhould rather put the higher powers in minde of that, <hi>Why tempt ye God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 15.10.</note> 
               <hi>to put a yoake upon the necke of the Diſciples, which neither our fathers, nor we are able to beare?</hi> wherein they are the leſſe excuſable, that they doe not pretend <hi>Peters</hi> chaire, or that their Church cannot erre.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:11723:19"/>
            <p>All which I urge, not to drive men to helpleſſe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition now, much leſſe to ſeparation; but to perſwade all to ſeeke and pray for an effectuall reformation. For can theſe things become neceſſary &amp; pleaſing to God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded by authority, which thus make the word &amp; ordinances of God of none effect, &amp; are an unneceſſary and a popiſh yoak, and only pretended to be done unto edifying?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> Indeed the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Let all things be done unto edifying.</hi> But theſe things as you have ſeene, doe not edifie, but hinder the free preaching of the Goſpell in divers particulars, as alſo diligent hearing, faith, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and other graces; nouriſh ambition, temporizing, lukewarmneſſe, and ignorance; and withall carie this miſchiefe along with them, that be they never ſo unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and hurtfull, yet God muſt not have one ſervant to manifeſt ſo much, no nor to ſpeake in his cauſe. For if any doe, preſently to choake him, they brand him with the name of a <hi>Puritan,</hi> and a factious fellow: and if that will not ſerve, they can ſuppreſſe him with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, he is troubled and ſilenced, the Church muſt bee deprived of him, for ſtumbling at a popiſh ceremony, though he be otherwiſe never ſo peaceable, ſincere, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, painfull, and powerfull: when Dioceſſan Biſhops were firſt ordained, they had not this power, much leſſe in ſuch caſes.</p>
            <p>In the booke of the ordering of Prieſts and Deacons, they ſay, <hi>there were alwaies Prieſts,</hi> that muſt needs bee Presbyters, <hi>in the Church:</hi> If ſo, what a mockery is it to retaine the name Prieſt, as an order of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and neither diſtinguiſh that name from the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Law, nor let them exerciſe the office of the Presbyters, which was as well to rule their owne flocks, as to preach, and adminiſter the Sacraments? what a mockery is it to ſtand ſo much on the ſurpleſſe, the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:11723:19"/> hood, tippet, and ſquare cap, worne with ſuch glory, and ſuperſtition by the Papiſts, and in the meane, by all theſe things to bring religion out of ſquare, and deprive the Church of her better ornaments, good Preachers, El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, hearers, faith, knowledge, humility, zeale, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graces? what a mockery is it to ordaine,<note place="margin">Can. 48.</note> 
               <hi>that no Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, or Miniſter, ſhall bee permitted to ſerve in any place, without examination, and admiſsion of the Biſhop of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, or Ordinarie, in writing under hand and ſeale.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. 51.</note> 
               <hi>That no ſtrangers ſhall preach in Cathedrall Churches, but ſuch as are allowed by the Archbiſhop, or Biſhop.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. 52.</note> 
               <hi>That the names of all Preachers ſtrangers, that ſhall preach in any Church, ſhall bee taken by the Churchwardens,</hi> &amp;c. when all this is extended againſt few, or none, but ſuch as ſtumble at ſome rites, or ceremonies, to keepe them from preaching, and have them ſilenced? and in the meane while divers ignorant and idle drones, non-reſidents, yea Arminian, and popiſh teachers, ſuch as Doctor <hi>Price</hi> of Weſtminſter, lately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, are admitted to have and hold the cure of ſoules, and the Biſhops uſe this their power to hinder the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from chooſing zealous Miniſters, that ſubſcribe to be their Paſtors, or helping Lecturers: they reckon ſuch dangerous: and if they have got admiſſion, they ſhall be watched, yea made offendors <hi>for a word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 29.21.</note> 
               <hi>and turned aſide for a thing of naught.</hi> If in the meane they will needs bee diligent, they may with much adoe preach the Goſpell, and apply it againſt Poperie, but not the whole counſell of God; not a word againſt growing Arminianiſme, much leſſe for the Elderſhip, or againſt the Hierarchie, and traditions.</p>
            <p>What a mockerie is it to appropriate unto themſelves and their Officials, all <hi>Eccleſiasticall diſcipline,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that ſacred and dreadfull power of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; when in the meane they exerciſe it againſt few, but
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:11723:20"/> ſuch as are againſt their hierarchie, rites, and ceremonies, or men that have failed to appear to anſwer for the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a ſhop doore on a holy day, or ſome ſuch triviall offence? If a man plead neceſſity, and want conſtrained him to it, or that God ſaith, <hi>Six dayes ſhalt thou labour,</hi> &amp;c. neither reaſon, nor the holy Scripture can be heard againſt their government, and traditions: but they know how to geere him out, like the proud phariſes, that ſaid, <hi>Thou wast altogether borne in ſinnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 9.</note> 
               <hi>and doſt thou teach us?</hi> And indeed an incorrigible ſwearer, fornicator, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, blaſphemer, or heretike, may more eaſily eſcape their power, then ſuch a Puritan, as they terme him. And if he offer to prove that in this, or any other thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to their government or ordinances, they are ſomewhat Antichriſtian; Doctor <hi>Lambe,</hi> or any like monſter, may live more peaceably, amidſt all his known abominations, then ſuch a wicked Puritan heretike, as they call him. And in the meane while, they are aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to make the name of a reformation as odious to all, as it is to themſelves, and even to glory in their Church, as the moſt pure and Apoſtolike that ever was ſince the Apoſtles; not counting it in thoſe Paſtors and people that zealouſly and religiouſly preach, and heare the word, to have it followed: for the Prelates would not have ſuch counted to be the Church of England, nor ſcarce of it; but themſelves aſſembled in a Synod, which they call the Church repreſentative; or as they are conſidered with all their traditions, and all the moſt conformable obſervers, and maintainers of them. Theſe make that Church that ſo glorifieth her ſelfe, like <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.17.</note> that ſaid, <hi>I am rich, and increaſed with goods, &amp; have need of nothing: and knew not that ſhee was wretched, and miſerable, and poore, and blinde, and naked.</hi> Wherein they that are ſo mighty in power, and ſo able to reward men,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:11723:20"/> cannot want flatterers and learned champions, and ſo the great places of the hierarchy ſerve to corrupt men, and to make them mould religion after ſuch mens pleaſures, as can advance them; like as wofull experience hath alſo ſhewed in the Arminians,<note place="margin">Iſa. 29.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>Their feare towards God hath beene</hi> long <hi>taught by the precepts of men:</hi> and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they as the Papiſts received not the love of the truth in matter of the Elderſhip, Hierarchie, traditions, ceremonies:<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.10.</note> therefore God gave them over <hi>to ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions, to beleeve</hi> popiſh and Arminian <hi>lies:</hi> and becauſe they received not the love of the truth againſt thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian errours, God that is ever juſt, muſt needs give them over to greater blindeſſe, and error.</p>
            <p>Such are the fruits of the Hierarchie, and the humane invention, and defence thereof. Reverend <hi>Hooker,</hi> as they call him, ſhall in thoſe caſes bee of more authority with theſe men, then St. <hi>Paul;</hi> ſo much are they wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the traditions and ceremonies of their Church. All theſe traditions, inventions, officers, Courts, and ſuperſtitious rites, were not invented, much leſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be received as lawes, in the time of the Fathers, as now by the Epiſcopall power: and if they were, there is (as was ſhewed) no reaſoning from the conſent or connivance of the Fathers, if the inſtitution bee not warrantable by Gods word. There were then divers things which had got beginnings in thoſe times, againſt which the Fathers did not much inveigh, becauſe they were then held indifferent, and not eſtabliſhed as ſince for matters of faith, and neceſſitie, as the primacy of the Pope, ſingle life of Prieſts, ſet faſts, deferring baptiſme till death, the uſe of ſalt, holy water, and divers other things in their rites; the antiquity whereof makes them never a whit the more lawfull.<note place="margin">Ioh 8.44.</note> 
               <hi>The devill was a ſeducer and a lyar from the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:11723:21"/>
            <p>Whether it were in a vaine policie of ſome Biſhops of thoſe times, the ſooner to draw Iewes and Heathen to Chriſtianity, as ſome of ours pretend the indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and wiſedome of uſing ſome Romiſh rites, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to draw Papiſts to Church, or for other like reaſons. Sure it is, that many inſtitutions of religion began in thoſe daies to be taken from the Iewes, and ancient hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, as divers have proved to the Papiſts, out of their owne authors. Among others, Mr. <hi>Derlingcourt,</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Reformed Church of Paris, in his booke of the Iubilee, ſhewes in it many things; to omit other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars:<note place="margin">Iubile of the reform. Chur. part. 2. c. 11.</note> 
               <hi>The whole Papall Hierarchie</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is founded on the example of the Iewes, who had their ſoveraigne Pontife, their ſacrificers, and their Levites, and among them divers orders, and functions. And that the Church of Rome hath founded her Hierarchie, and the diverſity of her orders on the example of the Iewes, beſides that the thing is cleere enough, the Author of the</hi> Canon Decretis <hi>acknowledgeth it: And</hi> Polidor. Virg. <hi>de invent rerum,</hi> lib. 4. cap. 5. &amp; 7. <hi>where he alſo confeſſeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Decree of Gratian part. 12. dift. 21.</note> 
               <hi>that the Romiſh Prieſts have borrowed of the Iewiſh Prieſts, the most part of their habits, &amp; that it is moſt evident, that the inſtitution is rather Hebraicall, then Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall. And indeed the Apoſtles were never cloathed in the habits of Biſhops, nor Popes.</hi> Reade on this ſubject, Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3. <hi>Myſteriorum Miſſae, lib. 1.</hi> and the Biſhop of Manda, <hi>Ration. divin. officior. lib. 3.</hi> And a little after. <hi>We have ſeene that the Church of Rome authorizeth her hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie on the example of the Iewes, but ſhee alſo avoucheth that it is a pagan invention, for the decrees of Gratian, after hee had repreſented the diverſitie of the Romane Clergie, compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of ſimple Priests, Archpriests, Biſhops, Archbiſhops, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, Metropolitanes, Patriarches, Popes, addeth, that this diverſitie proceedeth principally from the ancient Pagans, who had their Prieſts, their Archprieſts, &amp;c. a confeſsion which is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:11723:21"/> drawne from the Maſter of the Sentences,</hi> lib. 4. diſt. 24. lit. M. <hi>The Biſhop of Manda doth alſo acknowledge the ſame truth,</hi> Ration. divin. offic. lib. 2. c. 1. n. 22. <hi>But there is none more formall in this ſubject, then</hi> G. du Chol. <hi>who ſaith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">G. du Choul diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſ. of the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ancient Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans pag. 337. &amp; 335.</note> 
               <hi>That Romanes had another faſhion of making their priestly digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as the great Pontifes, the little Pontifes, Flamins, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamins: just ſo as we have the Pope, Cardinals, Biſhops, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, and Patriarchs, &amp;c. And if we here obſerve it curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, we know that many institutions of our religion are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and tranſlated from the ceremonies of the Egyptians, and Gentiles, as are the copes, and ſurpleſſe, the Priests ſhaven crownes, the bowing of the head to the Altar, the ſacrificall pompe, the muſicke of the Temples, adorations, prayers, and ſupplications, proceſsions, and Letanies, and many other things. which our Priests uſurpe in our mysteries.</hi> Of which indeed many are anciently aſſumed of Chriſtians; but that makes them never a whit the more lawfull. How little then doe they helpe themſelves, who ſay, the Church of England in her hierarchie, and ceremonies, is moſt like to the Church which was ſoone after the death of the Apoſtles, that is, if it were ſo, as it is not; for they had not ſuch dominion over Presbyters, nor ſuch Courts, Chancellors, Deanes, Officials, power in probates of Teſtaments, to governe, and command, give licences, and diſpenſations; nor ſuch rulcs, and canons to ſuſpend and ſilence about ſurpleſſes, ceremonies, &amp;c. nor yet ſuch ſervice, and ceremonies: and if they had, yet that were nothing, being thus invented, and received by the Papiſts, and after retained in the Engliſh reformation, either for policie, or for the profit and honour that comes by them. Many more zealouſly defend theſe, then they doe the Goſpell againſt Papiſts and Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Surely the Angell ſpeakes not of ſuch men, but rather of ſuch in the reformed Churches, as have aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:11723:22"/> theſe inventions,<note place="margin">Rev. 19.10 Eph. 1.13.</note> when he ſaith, <hi>I am of thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that have the testimony of Ieſus;</hi> which is to have the marke or ſeale of God in the forehead, by profeſſing they will receive no other doctrine, and religion, but what is rightly drawne from his teſtimony; as on the contrary, to profeſſe the Romiſh faith, and ſuperſtition, is to have the beaſts mark in the forehead by profeſſion, and any way to defend it, is to have it in the right hand by operation: and therefore though it ſeeme harſh to ſay, that the champions of the hierarchie, and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, have the mark of the beaſt, becauſe in other things they are Proteſtants; yet can it not be maintained, but that they are guilty of having ſome part and print of that marke, becauſe they obſtinately maintaine them againſt all proofes, ſhewing them to be popiſh, in favour Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, and Heatheniſh, againſt the word of God, and to make the ſame of no effect, in divers particulars. The wiſedome of God ſaith by the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>Rebuke them ſharply, that they may be ſound in the faith, not giving heed to Iewiſh fables, and commandements of men, which turne from the truth.</hi> So doe theſe in England, in divers reſpects. Becauſe while ſome Prelates and Miniſters make a noiſe and a bluſtring, with crying out againſt Puritans, and a great flouriſh with exalting the name and authority of the Church in ſuch caſes, and the ancient uſe of the dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſan and provinciall Biſhops, ordinances, and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; Princes and people thinke they ſerve God in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying her in them, and therefore ſtop their eares to all proofes to the contrary, and mocke at them (like the Biſhops, that both ſcorne, and ſuppreſſe them all) even as others did in the Church of Rome, in the ſame and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſes; who otherwiſe had never attained that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ſhe thereby got, nor to have her traditions, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and ſuperſtitious rites received for lawes: which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:11723:22"/> were the terrible fruits of mens blind obedience to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall Biſhops, and their power, and ordinances; which ever increaſed more and more, as they were more and more obeyed, and defended, to the great hinderance of the kingdome of God, and the due preaching and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of his word.</p>
            <p>And though in England the hierarchy and her tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and injunctions have not had ſo many and ſo bad fruits, becauſe it hath not reigned ſo long; yet as wee have ſeene for the time, they have beene, if not alike, yet very injurious to Gods kingdome, and the good of the Church. It helpes them not to ſay that ſome great Divines in other Churches have approved them, or counted them tollerable. For ſtrangers cannot ſo well ſee the fruits of them; and bee ſure, that if they were brought into the Reformed Churches of Germany and France, divers would bee found to receive them, and give arguments of their neceſſarie uſe, they are ſo full of honour, and profit. For we have lately ſeene it in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; and we know the Scriptures ſay,<note place="margin">Deut. 16.19.</note> 
               <hi>Gifts blinde the eyes of the wiſe.</hi> This made them thinke it a ſufficient au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that the ancient Church invented and uſed dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſan and provinciall Biſhops, though in a manner dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from ours; that not onely Councels, but even Emperours and Kings confirmed and augmented their authority, and that much good might bee done by the ſame.</p>
            <p>When firſt <hi>King Edward,</hi> and after <hi>Queene Elizabeth</hi> came in, the Nobles and people were almoſt all Papiſts, and it was thought they would bee the ſooner drawne to Church, if Biſhops, and their power and authority were retained, having ſtill their Courts, Chancelours, Officials, Deanes, Subdeanes, Quiriſters, Organs, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſſes, and other habits, the croſſe in baptiſme, knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:11723:23"/> at the receiving of the Sacrament, bowing toward the Altar, and divers other ceremonies. For this end alſo the forme of Common Prayer, &amp; Service was little altered, but taken out of the Maſſe-booke, and put into Engliſh: which makes many Papiſts in Germany and France ſay, ſure the Romiſh is the true and right religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, elſe the heretikes in England would never have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſo much of it: for ſome have avouched it to my face, that the ſervice there is nothing but the Maſſe in Engliſh: others, that it wants nothing but the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration. Theſe things thus retained, it was alſo thought that popiſh Kings and Princes would be the leſſe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; what marvell, ſeeing the Ieſuites themſelves are ſo well pleaſed with the ceremonies and ſervice, that I heard one of them (God is my witneſſe herein) make it his hope, that the maintenance of them againſt the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans,<note place="margin">Quovadis Sect. 4.</note> would make England the ſooner returne to Rome in the reſt. <hi>Mine eyes and eares</hi> (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi>) <hi>can witneſſe, with what approofe and applauſe divers of the Catholikes royall (as they are termed) entertained the new tranſlated Lyturgie of our Church.</hi> Which is the leſſe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,<note place="margin">Cambden in an. 1560</note> ſeeing Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the 4. ſending <hi>Vincentio Parpatia,</hi> Abbot of S. Saviours to <hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi> offered <hi>to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the Engliſh Liturgie by his authoritie, if ſhe would yeeld to him in ſome other things.</hi> Indeed it pleaſed them ſo wel that for the firſt eleven yeares of <hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. Cooke de Iure Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gis Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtico. Fol. 34.</note> 
               <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists came to the Engliſh Churches and ſervice,</hi> as the Lord <hi>Cooke</hi> ſheweth. All which things prove it to be a poore brag of ſome, who thinke it a good juſtification in the common prayer booke, that Papiſts have approved it; and could never finde any fault in it.</p>
            <p>As it is true that there are many godly and zealous men (and ſome others alſo, who thinking it a glory to be of their party, are more of faction, then well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:11723:23"/> knowledge, and love to Chriſt) againſt the forme, and ſome other things in the book of Common praier; So is it as true that there are many both of the Clergy and laity, and ſome both learned and godly, ſuch as ſincerely love the preaching, and power of the Goſpel, that yet hold the booke of Common prayer both tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, profitable, and neceſſarie, and are not willing to heare any thing to the contrary: and therefore God may ſay of our times, as of thoſe wherein <hi>Ieremy</hi> lived,<note place="margin">Ier. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>Run to and fro, and ſee now, if yee can finde a man that ſeeketh the truth.</hi> I would deſire ſuch to take a few things into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. Where firſt I muſt acknowledge, that though divers faults are found in the book of common prayer, which makes it ſo agreeable to the Papiſts; for there is ſcarce a Church papiſt in England that doth not applaud and admire it: yet doe I not finde it ſo corrupt as ſome would make it. In it wee finde this prayer: <hi>O God from whom all holy deſires, all just counſailes, and all good workes doe proceed, give, &amp;c.</hi> this is certainly tranſlated out of the Romiſh Liturgie, yet is it in it ſelfe ſo faultleſſe, that I will not diſpute againſt him that thinkes hee may daily ſay it, either with a congregation, or in private: and ſo many other of the prayers, that is, if he doe not the leſſe, but rather the more, hearken to Gods word in all points, otherwiſe his prayer will certainly be abominable.</p>
            <p>But if all the prayers be as uncorrupt, why doth Dr. <hi>Iackson,</hi> with the conſent and approbation of the Biſhops,<note place="margin">Pro. 28.9. Dr. Iackſon. 1. part,</note> alledge divers of them for points ſavouring of Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſme and Poperie? and if they bee ſo neceſſary to ſalvation, as ſome make them, other reformed Churches are but in an ill caſe, that have them not, ſo was the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church alſo, eſpecially for three hundred yeares. Howſoever what need is there ſo much to flatter the Papiſts, as to tranſlate prayers out of their Maſſe book,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:11723:24"/> and do ſo many things in ſervice after their forme when God ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.22. Iſa. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Obedience is better then ſacrifice, Who hath requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this at your hands?</hi> which are now ſo far from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them come the ſooner to Church, unles it be to continue papiſts there, and falſe brethren to us, that they hence draw arguments to ſtrengthen them in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſaying, ſure theirs is the true religion, or elſe theſe parts of it would not be ſo conſtantly defended againſt the puritans; and in the meane that kept out, which <hi>Queene Mary</hi> ordained ſhould be razed out of all bookes of Rites, uſed in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> 8, and <hi>Edward</hi> the 6,<note place="margin">Hiſt. of the Councel of Trent. pap. 385.</note> wherein God is prayed. <hi>To deliver the Kingdom from ſedition, conſpiracie, and the tyrannie of the Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can not other common praiers be made as good? The french Churches have ſome that are uſed, in the pulpit by him that preacheth, and no other, that ſo he may not make a ſufficient Religion, &amp; ſervice of praier, nor account the cure to be ſerved without preaching. In them they pray. <hi>Deliver thy Churches from the mouthes of ravening wolves and all hirelings, who ſeeke their owne ambition, and profit, and not the exaltation of thy holy name, and the ſalvation of the whole flock.</hi> This alſo is ordinary before ſermon to pray, <hi>that the word may be then prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, in that puritie and ſinceritie, wherein it was left by the Apoſtles and Prophets.</hi> So that the preaching of the word is not hindered by their praiers. Whereas in many Churches, they have nothing on the Lords day but the common prayer: which many both of the Clergie, and people doe ſo highy extoll, that they make <hi>an entrie Religion</hi> of it, and not only neglect, but even deſpiſe preaching in reſpect thereof. Many nonpreaching Miniſters make it the pretext of their idlenes, and others of their nonreſidence, and pluralities, ſaying the people
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:11723:24"/> have one to read prayers, and the ſervice is performed. And that (ſay many) is ſufficient, if they had no more. It is to no end to tell them that God ſaieth. <hi>My people are destroied, or lead into Captivity for lack of knowledge;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.6. Rom. 10.17.</note> that faith <hi>comes by-hearing,</hi> and preaching; that certaine of the praiers are for knowledge: for they yet dare ſay, it doth more hurt then good: therefore they are all for common praier: which divers worldlings, uſurers, drunkards, whoremongers and other earthly, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane people, ſecond, and confirme, making it their whole Religion, and admiring it above meaſure, becauſe it doth not tax, and touch their ſins, as preaching doth; it ſerveth not for doctrine, reproofe, correction, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, as preaching the ſcripture doth: which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have in contempt, and hinder, and ſlander the ſame, and all the trueſt freinds, and followers thereof: and yet in the meane while, they would not only be thought the better ſbjects, but the better Chriſtians, and the fitter to be Churchwardens; yea and to beare greater offices in the Church, and common wealth: they count themſelves more truly religious, then the greateſt preachers, and hearers, becauſe they thinke they love the common praier booke better, and it ſerves them for a Religion, and a cloake of ſcoffing perſecution, and ſome of them to be Church Papiſts, and falſe brethren, under the name of proteſtants: whereas if the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mò praier booke were not, or there were only ſuch like common praiers, as are uſed by the French, and dutch in the pulpit, they could not but make more profeſſion of love to preaching, and hearing of Gods word, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they would appeare to bee, either without Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or more open adverſaries of our Religion, and ſo leſſe dangerous.</p>
            <p>In the French and dutch Churches they are not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:11723:25"/> with ſuch dumbe Miniſters, nonreſidents, Church papiſts, and prophane mockers: they that have leaſt Religion ſpeake no hurt of knowledge, preaching, and hearing: for if they ſhould they know, all men would crie out of them, as of papiſts, or Atheiſts, and order would quickly be taken with them by the Elders: they could not paſſe as ours doe, for the better men, and fitter for offices. The Biſhops ſee all this, and yet favour them the more of the two, as being ever verie confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable, and leſſe dangerous to the <hi>Hierarchie:</hi> ſo carefull are they that there may be nothing in their Church like the <hi>Elderſhip</hi> ordained of God. Churchwardens, and ſidemen are but a mockerie of it, theſe places being given to all ſort of men, drunkards and others: when the parſon alſo is a tiplar, a nonreſident, or preacheth little, there is a flock ſtrangely governed. And thus the word of God is made of none effect by the <hi>Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie,</hi> &amp; the traditious thereof, and namely by the much defended,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.13.</note> and admired book of common praier: &amp; thus theſe ordinances of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> turne from the truth, as Tit. 1.13</p>
            <p>It wilbe objected the abuſe of any thing in Religion ſhould not take away the uſe of it, which you grant. I doe ſo, but that is in the things ordained of God, as the Elderſhip, the Lords prayer, the uſe of the Pſalmes and ſome formes of bleſſing,<note place="margin">Nomb. 6.23. Rom. 16.24. 1. Cor. 16.23.</note> like thoſe Nomb. 6.23. Rom, 16.24. Which being common prayers, ſerve to juſtifie the uſe of a few ſuch common praiers as may be in the reformed Churches: but not the hierarchie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ordained of God, nor a ſervice booke taken out of the Romiſh liturgie, in ſuch a time, and for ſuch reaſons, as it was: ſerving men for a whole Religion, and thus making the word of none effect. For if thoſe reaſons had beene good of drawing the papiſts the ſooner to Church &amp;c. there are not the ſame now, when almoſt all goe to Church; the Recuſants though many are
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:11723:25"/> nothing in compariſon of thoſe times; and by Romiſh ſubtiltie, the booke of ſervice is turned to doe hurt to our religion, as aboveſaid. Now to call for the uſe of the ſervice book and extoll it, is nothing elſe but to temporiſe with popelings to emulate knowledge, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and writing, and to provide one naile to drive out another, at leaſt in ſuch points as touch mens cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in doctrine, and practiſe: which was a ſleight uſed of old by the Romiſh clergie: for when the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates ſaw preaching diſcovered their errours, and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie; they to put off that, and yet to ſeeme no leſſe religious, fell to extoll the uſe of their ſervice, and maſſe, and cried out for devotion, peace, and obedience to the Church, and above all for praier; wherein divers flattering, and ambitious preachers, and even moſt of the Engliſh Biſhops themſelves, follow them apace, and that in theſe daies while men complaine of corruption in the clergie, and the increaſe of <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, witnes <hi>Dr. Couſens</hi> his couſening devotions, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Biſhops, and divers ſermons, Speeches, and practiſes of theirs to the like purpoſe: But marke what God ſaith; <hi>He that turneth away his eare, from the hearing of the Law, even his praier ſhal be abomination.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28.9.</note> What will become then of their devotion, who not only turne away their owne eares, but even the eares of others alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hearing the oracles of God, both in this point of the Elderſhip, and in thoſe maine points of the Goſpel, touching Gods free grace, and power in elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, converſion, perſeverance, &amp;c. It troubles them much that men ſhould have knowledge, preach, or write in theſe points, while in the meane they can let the contrarie doctrines paſſe in the books of the <hi>Appealer, Dr. Iackſon,</hi> and others: theſe trouble them not in a time when papiſts, &amp; <hi>Arminians</hi> ſtrive to infect Princes &amp;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:11723:26"/> people with ſuch Pelagian and popiſh opinion? God commands <hi>to contend earneſtly for the faith, which was once delivered to the ſaints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude. 3.</note> they yet preſume that it may be forbidden in theſe caſes, ſo the people be ſtirred up to praier, peace and obedience to the Church. I know the daylie exerciſe of praier may be much urged: but by whom? by men that ſincerely love preaching, and hearing in all things that God hath revealed, &amp; taught; and do not ſet the ordinances of God one againſt an other, that is, doe not urge praier as enemies of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in many points, like the papiſts; norn aemula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, as thoſe that oppoſe praier to preaching, to eat out knowledge, and bring-in blind devotion: theſe have but a forme of Godlines, and ſcarce that, wee had need to pray continually that God would purge, &amp; rid the Church of ſuch hipocriticall wolves.</p>
            <p>It is a principle of Gods covenant of grace, <hi>that he will give us Paſtors according to his owne hart, that ſhall feed us with knowledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iur. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>and understanding:</hi> knowing, that is, a curſe to bee led by blind guides, &amp; left in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: they yet preſume that Paſtors may be hindered, and knowledge forbidden in theſe things, ſo people be but incited to building and repairing of temples, praier, &amp;c. As if God would heare ſuch as will not heare him, nor ſuffer others to heare him in ſuch points, but pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, &amp; terrifie ſuch as produce any proofes in ſuch caſes, either in print or pulpit: which is not to prevent ſchiſme, and preſumptuous curioſitie, as they pretend, but to make way for <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> and poperie, and againſt all oppoſers to ſay with them in the Pſalme. <hi>Let us breake their bonds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and caſt away their cords from us:</hi> and ſhould therefore be anſwered, with that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God to hearken unto you more than unto God, judge ye,</hi> we reade of ſome
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:11723:26"/> that devoured widdowes houſes under colour of long praiers, I pray God theſe doe not devoure Churches, &amp; ſtates, yea the faith it ſelf, under colour of long praiers,<note place="margin">Math. 23.14.</note> and ſtanding, ſoe much for the uſe of the common praier booke as the Papiſts did for theirs. For are not ours men as well as they? And hath not England alſo an <hi>Hierarchie,</hi> and many places of honor, and profit in it? Are they not oft beſtowed on ſuch as ſet the faireſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours on the <hi>Hierarchie,</hi> and ceremonies, and oft on ſuch as have flattered the <hi>Duke,</hi> and ſuch other maſqued Agents for <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> and <hi>Poperie?</hi> And ſo they ſerve as baites to corrupt, and make the ambitious, forme and mold Religion to the opinion, and pleaſure of ſuch as can advance, and make them double beneficed men.</p>
            <p>The Cardinall of Monte, (Prince Legate in the Counſell of Trent, under <hi>Paul</hi> the 3,<note place="margin">Hiſtorie of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Trent pag. 191.</note> and after created Pope by name of <hi>Iulius</hi> the 3,) hearing the complaints againſt nonreſidents, ſaid. <hi>That the abſence of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, and other Curates from their Churches is the cauſe all the miſcheifes of the Church. For the Church may be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a ſhip, the ſinking whereof is aſcribed to the abſent Pilot, that ſhould governe it, if he were prefent. It ſhewed to them that hereſies, ignorance, and diſſolution doe raigne in the peolple, and bad manners, and vices in the Clergie, becauſe the Paſtors being abſent from the flock, no man hath care to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct thoſe, or correct theſe: whence ignorante, and unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Ministers have beene promoted to Cures, and Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wricks; for in regard they neede not execute their dutie in perſon, no fitnes is neceſſarie.</hi> Divers Prelates following him. But the Biſhop of Veſone ſaid, <hi>that the reſiding of Biſhops, is notable to make the Clergie live holy; for that beſides the general exemption of all Regulars, everie Chapter hath one, and there be few particular Preiſts that want it.</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:11723:27"/> The moſt followed his opinion, that it was neceſſarie to command reſidence, <hi>And to take away exemptious, pluralities, and diſpenſations that hindred it:</hi> But it was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeene, that if, this were don, the authoritie of the Pope, and Cardinals would be overthrowne: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was ever hindered, though the Biſhops laboured to regaine their power to ſuperintend, and ſhake of the Popes yoake, by offering to prove that Reſidence, and juriſduction of Biſhops are <hi>de jure divino:</hi> for the Regulars, were ſtill protected, as champious of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie, and the Popes authoritie, and diſpenſations were cunningly reſerved. Indeed much was reſtored to the Biſhops in doubtfull tearmes to ſuperinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, as Delegates of the Apoſtolick ſea: but they could not regaine all, becauſe it was perceived that would ſhake the greatnes of the Pope, and Cardinals, reforme them, make them reſide, and the Biſhops would be made ſo many Popes in their owne <hi>Dioceſſes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 170 219.496. &amp; 497.501 &amp; 502.</note> 
               <hi>For if it were once decided, that they had the Charge from Christ to governe the Church, it would be decided alſo, that they have from him authoritie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsarie for it, which the Pope could not reſtraine.</hi> They tooke this to bee proved by that Acts. 20.17. <hi>Take heede therefore unto your ſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 20.17.20.</note> 
               <hi>and to all the flock, over which the holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops.</hi> Which indeed is againſt the Pope, and all dioceſſan Biſhops, as being ſpoken to the preſbiters: this and other places abovementioned being <hi>their letters patents,</hi> to governe the Church to the worlds end. Therefore when the Biſhops had almoſt gained their cauſe by pluralitie of voices, the Pope, and Cardinals cryed out againſt it, <hi>Every one thinking he did already ſee Rome emptie of Prelates, and deprived of all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, and eminence that the Cardinals ſhould be excluded from haveing Biſhopwricks, and all from pluralities, that no Biſhop, or Curate might have an office in Rome, nor the Pope
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:11723:27"/> diſpence in ſuch things, which are moſt principle in his power: ſo his authoritie ſhould be much diminiſhed, and that of the Biſhops enlarged, therefore they thought theſe novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties aymed to make many Popes;</hi> And afterward, they would neither have that point of reſidence, nor that whether Biſhops be inſtituted by Chriſt and ſuperiour to Preiſts to be diſputed, and concluded, though many Biſhops oft laboured therein.</p>
            <p>But the Biſhops of England, takeing the later for granted, have what thoſe others could not attaine: they have no Pope over them to take away their power, unles peradventure ſometime ſuch a one as the Duke of Buck: was, who after his way increaſeth, but doe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves diſpence with pluralities and uphold nonreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents and <hi>Arminians</hi> as the ſureſt champions of their hierarchic, ſuch as doe not ſo much make ready a Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie for Chriſt as Antichriſt. They ſuperintend over all preachers in their <hi>Dioceſſes,</hi> with ſuch unlimited power as the Trent-Biſhops could never attaine, that all muſt ſubſcribe to them and their conſtitutions, and none may preach, diſpute, or write for the Elderſhip, and againſt the hierarchie, and Arminians, nor ſcarce againſt other poperie; which makes men ſay; they are Popes within themſelves, and this power cannot reſt heere, it wilbe more Antichriſtian, if it be not taken away. The French Churches though oft troubled with wars, and hurliburlies are yet in better caſe herein, ſeeing they may write, print, and preach any divine truth, though moſt repugnant to the Popiſh Biſhops, that live among them, and cannot hinder them.</p>
            <p>Indeed he that conſiders it well, ſhall find that though the Conncel of <hi>Nice,</hi> made the Biſhops of <hi>Rome Patriarchs;</hi> yet they did not for 300 yeares after raigne ſo much over Presbiters; in ſuch caſes as the Engliſh Biſhops doe.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:11723:28"/>
            <p>Let us not wonder then when wee ſee that many great Schollars, &amp; ſom that have beene good preachers, when they have attained theſe great places, and double benefices, or are in poſſiblitie of comming to them, or haveing living under them, ſhould bee ſo loth ſo ſee any thing againſt them. <hi>For gifts blind the eyes of the wiſe,</hi> and their ignorance in points of nonreſidencie, the hierarchie, and traditions, is a puniſhment on them for their frowardnes, wilfull blindnes, ambition and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes; at leaſt for making tradition ſufficient au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in ſuch caſes. For indeed few men, ſuch is the weaknes of corrupt nature, can be willing to ſee that, which would hinder them from ſubſcribing ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a good living, or make them ſorrie they had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, or to be adverſe to that, againſt which they may not be ſuffered to ſpeake, much leſſe, to preach, or write, and leaſt of all to reforme, or amend: as alſo becauſe if they ſtir never ſo little in theſe caſes, they are ſure to looſe their liveings, to bee by the Biſhops, and their champious ſilenced, with ſcoffes, power, and terror, in ſtead of good arguments; and ſo to be in more danger then popiſh Preiſts and Ieſuits. Some therefore will have no knowledge at all in ſuch points, leaſt it bring them to miſerie, others thinke it beſt to keepe their knowledge to themſelves, leave the amendement to God, and in the meane doe the beſt good they can by their miniſterie in other matters: but the moſt know little of this argument,<note place="margin">Math. 13.11.</note> becauſe it is not given them of God to know it. They therefore thinke all theſe things to bee lawfull, neceſſary, and the obedience an acceptable ſervice to God, becauſe commanded by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and in ſome ſort ordained, and uſed by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Church. This is as if they ſayd, Kings, and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods may command what they lift in the Church:
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:11723:28"/> which is as good a warrant, as they had of old that made a calfe in Horeb, frequented the high places, or Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams Calves, eſtabliſhed by authoritie.</p>
            <p>It is nothing that many of theſe men are learned, and of great knowledge, and good conſcience in other matters. For God ſaith: <hi>For as much as this people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 29.15.</note> 
               <hi>draw nigh to me with their mouth, and with their lips doe honour me, but have removed their hart far from me, and their feare towards me is taught by the precepts of men, therefore behold I will proceede to doe a marveilous worke among this people, even a marveilous worke, and a wonder: for the wiſdom of their Wiſemen ſhall periſh, and the underſtanding of their prudent men ſhall be hid.</hi> Wiſdom ſhould decay in ſome, and others ſhould not dare to ſhew it. God that is ever juſt, muſt much rather doe it now to our learned, and Wiſemen, ſeing he hath <hi>blotted out the handwriting of ordinances, which was contrarie to us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>and tooke it out of the way nayling it to his croſse.</hi> For hath he taken them away that himſelf ordained, that men may loade us with others? doth Chriſt ſay,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.24.</note> 
               <hi>I will put upon you none other burden, but which ye have already, hold faſt till I come?</hi> And ſhall men bee perſwaded that they may impoſe ſuch as he never ordained, and as make the word of none effect? The hierarchie is not only in it ſelf a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ordinance, but the Biſhops ſeeme to looke to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but to uphold it, and ſuch canons, traditions, ceremonies and ſervice, as it hath invented, or received from men. Sometime hereticks, as Anabaptiſts, Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or the like, and ſometimes perſons, ſtained with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious adulterie, or Simonie, are by them, and their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficials, queſtioned, and caſt out, as in the Church of Rome. But theſe things, to rare, both may be, and are much better performed by Elders in the congregations, where ſuch delinquents live; as alſo againſt all noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:11723:29"/> drunckards, blaſphemers, ſwearers, mockers, and other profane perſons: of whom Biſhops nor theire of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficials neither doe, nor well can heare any thing; and if they doe: it is not amended, and therefore Dioceſſan Biſhops ſerve not to looke to them, nor to nonreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, nor to hinder the growth of Arminianiſme, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, &amp;c. they can ſee them increaſe, and never ſtir againſt them; yea religion to be corrupted more, and never move to helpe it: but hinder them that would.</p>
            <p>If ſome others be better affected, and would ſtir if they durſt: this is Gods mercie to his people, who knowes, that if all Biſhops were as corrupt, many would be ready to thinke, ſure they hold the popiſh, or Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian religion will ſerve to ſalvation, and they are wiſer then wee. God therefore provides that ſome Biſhops, and conformiſts ſhould a little diſtaſt their Romiſh prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, though they doe little, or no good againſt them, but in the meane they can not bate, a little of their hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie, traditions, and ceremonies, ordained, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by men; though they be proved to bee moſt injurious, and repugnant to Gods Kingdome, and the true peace of Chriſtian Churches, ſtates, and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, making the word of God, wherein their wel-beeing conſiſts, of none effect, this is the order they preſerve. No proofes of holy Scripture can be heard againſt them, either by the Biſhops, by the privie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, or by our Princes, and Parliaments: but their feare toward God is, in theſe things, taught by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of men, what marvaile then if not only in theire wiſeſt councellors, but even in their moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Clergie, wiſdome bee hid, and periſhed in divers points, and they become the ſcorne of all nations, and religions, for upholding religion in ceremonie only, &amp; letting it in the ſubſtance thereof fall dayly at home, and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:11723:29"/> abroade, &amp; thoſe of the papiſts and Arminians increaſe? If they had not ſuch a hierarchie ſuch ceremonies, and ſervice to defend, and ſerve them for an entire Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or a cloake of one, they could not for ſhame but defend the faith, and religion it ſelf, and their brethren that profeſſe it, which ſeeing they do not, what wonder if God plague them, not only with peſtilence, famine, and ſhamefull foiles in war, but even with ſpirituall plagues, that their governers both ſpirituall, and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, ſhould not ſee the things <hi>that belong to their peace, but have them hid from their eyes,</hi> and turne religion into pollicie, ſuch poore policie, as ſerves to couſen the land of her religion, and her friends of true helpe when they have moſt need of it, and moſt truſt to her; and to provoke the moſt high to bee their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, while they ſeeke to pleaſe his enemies? For the Spaniards and French have gotten aide of men, muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſhipping againſt thoſe of the reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>The Proteſtants in other countries that thinke they may ſpeake boldy, becauſe they have ſmarted for tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting to the Engliſh Say, that all this ſhewes them to bee of a mixed, or middle Religion, part of the Romiſh, in ſervice, and ceremonies, which are moſt defended, part of the Reformed in points of faith, leſſe regarded, and part of the Arminians lately received, or tollerated; that as middle Counſailes, and courſes doe uſually diſpleaſe both parties and give ſatiſfaction to neither, ſo hath it beene in the Counſailes and courſes of the Engliſh tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Religion, and the defence thereof. For though they ſomewhat pleaſe the papiſts, yet they ſatiſfie them not; but only imbolden them to get greater advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, for their Religion, to encroach, demand, practiſe, and by degrees prevaile by corrupting ſuch luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:11723:30"/> newters: that all theſe things are the fruits of the Engliſh hierarchie, and traditions, the Achans and Babyloniſh garments that trouble Iſrael; an hierarchie, and traditions, which taking their greateſt authoritie from Romiſh uſurpation, and ſuperſtition, bring forth ſuch Proteſtants; and which therefore is a Church plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted accordingly. For, ſay they, in England it hath beene, and is taken for a ſufficient converſion from po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie to come to the Church to the ſervice, and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: whereas in France, and other reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, before any papiſt is received and counted a prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, he is preſented in the congregation before the preacher, who aſketh him queſtion to this purpoſe. Firſt whether he hold the doctrine taught in the old &amp; new Teſtament to be Gods, and ſufficient to ſalvation? 2ly. whether he hold that the reformed Churches teach and hold the ſame doctrine in theire Religion, and he deſire to bee of it? 3 whether he hold the Pope to bee Antichriſt, and the Church of Rome the whore of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon? And ſo he conſenting to all this is received with joy; and there is no danger, that he ſhould be falſe, or popiſh, who makes this profeſſion, whereas in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, where allare admitted without any ſuch profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they may be true, or falſe, as they liſt. If they doe but come to the Church to the ſervice, &amp; ſacrament, though they ſecretly favour the Romiſh religion, &amp; it appeare to many in their practiſe, they may nevertheles be choſen parliament men, &amp; if they doe but take the oath of alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, as verie many papiſts have donne, who dares queſtion them? which is the reaſon there hath beene ſo much diſturbance in all the late aſſemblies of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo little fruit by them.</p>
            <p>Some, ſay they, not only in private pariſhes but ever in the court have come to church, like <hi>He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry Earle of Northa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> he Duke of Buck: &amp; others, and have favoured the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:11723:30"/> hierarchie, &amp; ſervice, ſpake well of them, &amp; of ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s bookes &amp; ſermons as little or nothing repugnant to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie; and for it were content to bee reckoned prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, that ſo they might get offices, honours, truſt, and power in great affaires, make ſome pretences for the good of our Religion, or the ſtate, but ſecretly carrie them for the advancement of the Romiſh cauſe. To ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it the better, and withall to ſave themſelves from danger, theſe, ſay they, beeing great, and able to helpe others to offices, and honour, plant ſuch about Kings, as themſelves are, and have had enow to applaude, ſecond, and juſtifie them in their proceeding: for as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith. <hi>A little leaven leaveth the whole lumpe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> how ſoever theſe, getting to be the Major and predominant part, will in time worke that there ſhal be no other but ſuch, unles perhaps ſome that are neither hot, nor cold in religion, or being poore, or leſſe potent, are forced for their owne private intereſts, to be ſilent, &amp; in time to depend on them, or beſwaied by them; and then they all, thus ingaged in any cauſe, are prone to juſtifie theire owne acts for good policies, and there is ſo little hope of getting ſounder men into their places, that it muſt needes bee as hard and dangerous to convince them, as for an inhabitant of Rome to convince that Church of any errour; a Parliament of wiſe men ſufficeth not to doe it: which hath beene the loſſe of the Palatinate, and the cauſe of all the evill our Religion hath ſuffered in Bohemia, Germanie, Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; at home. Eor ſay the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne proteſtants, if the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> &amp; the French had not beene, ſure they had ſuch freinds in England, they durſt never have attemtped that they did: that they that are ſuch, or flatter ſuch as are much infected with avarice, ambition, &amp; luſt, muſt needes be blinde in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things, eſpecially in the matter of the hierarchies;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:11723:31"/> wherein the devill labours to keepe them more blind then others, that ſo they may be unfit judges in the cauſe, and he may thereby ſet up traditions, to make the word of none effect, eftabliſh the tyrannie of the Biſhops in the Church againſt the <hi>Elderſhip,</hi> and all the friends thereof, keepe men lukewarme, and newters, if not thus falſe betweene Chriſt and Antichriſt; and ſo make way to bring England againe to Romiſh errour, or ſomwhat as bad: that ſuch Lords were ever in grace with the Biſhops, and the Biſhops with them, becauſe it troubles them not to have fellowſhip with Church pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts; ſo unlike are they to Saint Iohn, that would not come in the bath where <hi>Cerinthus</hi> was; that divers chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines &amp; preachers alſo, ſet up, &amp; fitted for their turnes, ſeeing them able to advance whom they would, have for their favour, broached, &amp; maintained, Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and popiſh tenets, wreſting the Articles, and the very Scriptures to confirme them: and thus ſay they, the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh hierarchie, and ſervice bring forth ſuch counſellors, and proteſtants, and ſuch counſellours bring forth ſuch Biſhops and Chaplaines. For if Princes or their favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites be but corrupted in religion, they cannot want flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, both of the Clergie and others to corrupt, and be corrupted, to conforme, and be conformed to them. For one that is againſt them they ſhall have hundreds with them, as in <hi>Ahabs</hi> time: ſo miſerable a thing it is, when they will not conforme their opinions to Gods word, but it to their policies and opinions, as one ſaid to <hi>Micajah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings. 22 13.</note> 
               <hi>The words of the Prophete declare good unto the King with one mouth, let thy word I pray thee be like the word of one of them. Constantius</hi> fell into Arianiſme, &amp; the <hi>Rivers and fountaines,</hi> the Biſhop and teachers were corrupted.</p>
            <p>To omit other inſtances, this deſire of authoritie ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:11723:31"/> and precedence, was the bane of the Church of Rome, who being drunke with that poiſon, and thereby ſwolme with a monſtrous greatnes, gave the cup to others: a cup that all nations are but to prove to drinke of. And indeed ſo much doe the favour of Princes and honours more then all other gifts, <hi>blind the eyes of the wiſe,</hi> and bring them to temporiſing, and ſpirituall igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that it may be counted a worke of Gods ſpeciall grace, that any that ſeeke, or attaine wealth, honour, and authoritie ſhould have the true knowledge and feare of God, ſeeing as Paul ſaith of them, that <hi>wil be rich,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 9.6</note> ſo it may be ſaid of them that wil be honourable, and great <hi>they fall into temptations and ſnares, and many fooliſh, and noyſome lusts that drowne men in perdition.</hi> And indeed ſuch doe commonly ſo abound in ſenſualitie that it may be ſaid of the moſt part of them.<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.20.</note> 
               <hi>Man being in honour, hath no understanding but is compared to the beasts that periſh.</hi> For nothing makes a man more like a beaſt then ſpirituall ignorance, and ſenſualitie. Nothing makes a man more ignorant in ſpirituall things, nor more ſenſuall, then thirſt after great places. <hi>Libido domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi beſtia ferociſsima.</hi> It is with this luſt after honour, as with that of uncleannes, the mind is ſo take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> up with it, that there is little roome for better thoughts, and the ſpirit of God will not dwell in that ſoule, which is filled with ſuch vainities, growes more and more emptye of grace. For ſurely many are caſt away <hi>by the deceitfulnes of Balaams wages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And God knowes that it is too manifeſt that many in the Church of England have beene made drunke with thoſe Romiſh dignities, and rewards that remaine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; that men bewitched with theſe, or the deſire of them, ſtumble into Arminianiſme, and other errours, at the pleaſure of them that can advance them: ſuch are
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:11723:32"/> the fruits of thoſe great places in the Hierarchie. For though the Duke were oft accuſed in Parliament, as an open favourer of Arminianiſme, and a ſecret practiſer by that, and other meanes to advance Romiſh Religion, &amp; other notorious crimes; yet many divines continued his conſtant freinds, and advocates, and have directly, or indirectly, maintained, &amp; propagated the ſame opinion and which is moſt miſerable, the cheife of that faction, being Biſhops and heads of Colledges, are they which now beare greateſt ſway in Religion, governe the Church of England, ſilence, and trouble whom they liſt, and in a manner give lawes to the whole Church in his Majeſties Dominions. Neither can it be better til <hi>Achan</hi> be found out, the corrupting, and Romiſh places of the hierarchie, and ſuch unprofitable traditions, and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies taken away; but ever worſe and worſe. For theſe things that were at firſt held indifferent, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to make Papiſts come the ſooner to Church, and to keepe unitie, and uniformitie, are now got into the place of the Scriptures, the <hi>Appealer</hi> alleadgeth the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> wreſted, and <hi>Dr. Iackſon</hi> certaine clauſes of the booke of comon praiers for Arminianiſme, with ſuch authoritie, as if they were the words of the Apoſtles; making the Church of England to meane what they liſt, and her meaning, or rather theirs, to be ſufficient au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in points of faith againſt them that bring Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to the contrarie, as the Church of Rome did of old, to eſtabliſh her tenets, and when theſe, and the like have beene queſtioned in Parliament, ſome to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage others to follow them, have counſailed to reward them, with Biſhopricks, denaries, Maiſterſhips of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.14.</note> or fat benefices, wherein they deale like <hi>Balaam that taught Balack to laie a ſtumbling block before the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael.</hi> For when divines ſee theſe thus rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:11723:32"/> this workes upon corrupt nature, which being prone to covetuouſes, and ambition, firſt makes the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences ſeeme ſmall, or not worth oppoſition, and then drawes the mind to run headlong into the ſame opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to thinke they doe well enough in the confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie. Hence alſo it comes that though forraigne Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and States, have oft deſired aide of England, that it would joine with them in ſerving the Pope, and his champions, as they ſerved them: nothing was ever ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually enterpriſed by the Engliſh; becauſe ſuch Courtiers as ſecretly favoured Rome have ever beene flattered by the Biſhops and Clergie, when the <hi>Palatinate</hi> ſhould have beene defended, and after recovered, by the ſwotd; theſe flatterers hindered it, by crying out of wars of Chtiſtian againſt Chriſtian, and ſaying it would bring in the Turke; that it were better all ſhould joyne againſt him, and ſpeake leſſe of the <hi>Romiſh Antichriſt,</hi> or <hi>Romes ruine,</hi> as alſo by extolling peace, and <hi>King Iames</hi> his indeavouts by Embaſſages, and treaties; which all men ſaid would come to nothing, and but make the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries to gaine time, deceive us, and grow more reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, cruell and mightie.</p>
            <p>And indeed it is impoſſible that the Engliſh Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie ſhould ever ſeeke Romes ruine, and not rather hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it all they can, becauſe the great places thereof are Romiſh, and a Dioceſſan Biſhop (as they are now) is no other then the Pope of a ſhire or province: and to ſhew reaſons why Rome ſhould bee ruined, were to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue againſt themſelves, trench upon their owne hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, and ſeeke to ruine it. They teach that their Hier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie, and <hi>Rites</hi> ought to be maintained: now the Romiſh is but an exceſſe in theſe things: which the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie perceiving can find no reaſon, why men ſhould bee ſo hot againſt Rome. The Hierarchie of the Old
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:11723:33"/> fathers was poſitive, the Engliſh is comparative, the Romiſh ſuperlative for as ſome have proved, if you grant the one to be lawfull, the other followes to bee as lawfull, ſave in the degree of impietie, as in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween fornication, and adulterie, or inceſt. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is that Biſhops cannot endure that Princes, and Nobles ſhould know the charter of the <hi>Elders,</hi> nor the miſcheife of the Hierarchie, that they beare more with Church papiſts, and whoremongers, then any ſuch pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanicall ſpirits, with groſſe ignorance, then ſuch know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, with ſuch as would ſet up poperie, then ſuch as would pull downe the Hierarchie, or that of Rome. If ſuch a one as the Duke hindered wars with Rome, or her chife champion the Spaniard, they wilbe his helpers ſo he will but ſtick to them againſt the freinds of the Elderſhip.</p>
            <p>And therefore the Hierarchie, and traditions with doctrine and arguments that maintaine them, are like the great river <hi>Euphrates,</hi> that hindred the ſacking of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> For heathen Babylon, lying on the one ſide of <hi>Euphrates,</hi> betweene <hi>Aſsiria,</hi> and <hi>Chaldea,</hi> was fortified by that river. So that <hi>Cirus</hi> the firſt vanquiſher thereof had not wonne it, but by a device of drayning the river above, by ſundrie artificiall ſluces, giveing his men in charge, whom he left before the Cittie, that when they ſhould obſerve the river to be decreaſed, and fourdable, they ſhould preſently take the opportunitie to wade over, and ſuddenly ſurpriſe <hi>Babylon.</hi> And the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie I ſay is like this river, for Biſhops and teachers with their doctrines are called <hi>rivers,</hi> and <hi>fountaines.</hi> Divers of theſe rivelets meeting in one make a great river, as many of them in a generall councell make a ſea of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, canons, and traditions: the Engliſh hierarchie therefore having but a few Biſhops, and fewer canons,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:11723:33"/> and traditions, then any popiſh Kingdom, can not bee called a ſea, but is a great <hi>river,</hi> and as a river oft parteth two Kingdomes, or provinces, pertaketh of both ſoiles, watereth them both and keepes the one from invading the other: ſo dothe the Hierarchie and the doctrines, and traditions thereof, which miſtically lieth both to the Proteſtant and Romiſh ſhores, watereth both, is as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and helpefull to Papiſts, as to the reformation, if not more: the great power, and places thereof are Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh; ſo are the traditions, canons, and arguments they uſe to defend it, they ſerve as well for the Papiſts, as for the Engliſh Biſhops; for indeed they ſpring out of that <hi>ſea,</hi> out of the which the beaſt <hi>aroſe,</hi> who alwaies allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the ancient cuſtomes and counſells, and they natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally run againe into the ſame, as rivers through many windings, find way into the ſea. Nothing lieth ſo newtrally betweene the Romiſh, and reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, as the Hierarchie, and the traditions thereof, unles perhaps the Lutheran Religion, which hath affinitie with it, and that nothing doth more fortifie Rome, and hinder the ruine thereof, this whole worke doth mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. And as a river doth water the bancks, townes, caſtles, and mannors that lie upon it, ſo doe theſe water the noblitie, and people, who delight to dwell on theſe ſhores, and drinke of theſe waters, which coole, or quench their zeale againſt miſticall <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſo fill them, with ignorance, and neutralirie, that they reliſh them better then the waters of the ſanctuarie, which are thoſe of the Elderſhip, and in requitall ſend into her thoſe land waters, which comming to them from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or ſpringing out of their grounds, fall into this ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and make it ſwell with a terrible greatnes, and theſe land waters are riches, and authoritie: which ſtreames muſt bee exhauſted or turned an other way, before Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon can be deſtroyed.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:11723:34"/>
            <p>I am not ſo confident is to make this a full expoſition of the <hi>ſixt viall,</hi> which yet is not the leaſt probable, ſeeing that things are rather to bee miſtically, then lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally underſtood. But ſure it is, that ſome have thought, that as without England there is little hope, that the Proteſtants ſhould prevaile, &amp; not rather be dayly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, as heretofore they have beene. So the Biſhops with their traditions, and practiſes, are the greateſt hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derances of true unitie, and confederacie among all proteſtant Princes and States, that England doth not ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually joyne with them againſt Antichriſt, and his champions; Papiſts therefore nouriſh the Engliſh Hier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archie, and all helpes thereof, knowing, that the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall authoritie, is at ſuch emnitie with the Elderſhip, that they can never be ſo true freinds of religion as to ſeeke unitie, and confederacie with Churches governed by <hi>elders,</hi> that all ſuch Princes and States, as Kings of the Eaſt and Citizens of the new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> may joyne to make the whore deſolate. Experience ſhewes that they have hindered it, and ſo are like, ſo long as the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie ſtands, and the waters thereof run with ſo ſtronge a ſtreame. Theſe therefore muſt be dried up by true light, knowledge, and zeale, ere God can be well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or the Church have hope of victorie. And ſure they ſhalbe taken away;<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> for Chriſt ſaith <hi>Every branch that beareth not fruite in me he taketh away;</hi> they therefore that ſtand for them doe in effect ſhew themſelves Romes freinds, and the Churches enemies, as the Arminians and popelings doe.</p>
            <p>There are three things that breede all the ſtir in the world, and hinder Romes ruine. 1 The greatnes of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which is nouriſhed by the Romiſh Clergie, and that Clergie by it, and that hath made ſome think this houſe, and the power, and riches thereof, to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:11723:34"/> bee the miſticall river <hi>Euphrates,</hi> which muſt be exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, or turned an other way, before Rome can be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; which is well begun by <hi>the King of Sweden.</hi> 2. Want of true unitie, and confederacie amongſt Proteſtant Princes and States againſt the common Adverſaries of Religion: for this hath emboldened the Pope, the howſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and others to attempt ſo much as they have, to ſubvert all by power, and policie. 3. The pernicious power, offices and greatnes of <hi>Dioceſſan,</hi> and Provinciall Biſhops, and other Clergie men, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe good effects in the two former, and makes bothe the Spaniard and Church of Rome to have ſtronge parties in all the greateſt Kingdoms in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, and even in England it ſelf, though Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in profeſſion. And ſuch Prelates indeed are a ſtronger fort to the great whore, then the howſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which if it be a fort, theſe yet are the deepe ditch, or more that goes about it; the great river that ſtrengthens both it, &amp; the Church, &amp; Cittie of Rome: the bankes of this river muſt be cut, the ſtreame of theire power and riches let out and dried up, ere any great good can be donne.</p>
            <p>It is a thing that will ſerve to aſtoniſh the ages to come, that any reformed Chriſtian; much leſſe thoſe that are reckoned, and ſo ſhould be, of the wiſer ſort, as Counſellours of eſtate, Nobles, Divines, &amp; many others, that ſeeme to have a greater ſhare of preeminence, wit, and learning, then of true knowledge, honour, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in ſuch caſes, ſhould ſtand ſo ſtedfaſtly in the maintenance of dioceſſan Biſhops, and traditions, and other wordly dignities, honours, and revenues, which the Clergie have obtained, beſides thoſe that are given to the Miniſters of Chriſt in the Goſpel. Wherein though it be true that all their defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, doe not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:11723:35"/> take the marke of the Beaſt, becauſe all that defend them, doe it not on purpoſe to helpe the Pope, and Church of Rome, or with the more eaſe to bring-in poperie, as ſome have ſaid of the late Duke, and his fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which indeed is to have the <hi>marke</hi> ſecret in the right hand: nor wholly, becauſe ſome that ſtand for Dioceſſan Biſhops, and theire traditions, which are po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, and tend to poperie, doe nevertheles hate other points of Poperie: yet doe they take it partly, in effect, and by conſequence, and in a way which is a ſtep, helpe, and introduction to all poperie: which cannot but bee <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 14.9.</note> dangerous, eſpecially when like Papiſts they will not ſee it, or ſeeing it, will not deſiſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt becauſe Antichriſt, and they are of one, and the ſame broode, and ofſpring, of one, and the ſame foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, his riſing was their riſing, and their traditions, and ceremonies are his; they had them from him, every Dioceſſan Biſhop is now a pettie Pope in his Dioceſſe. For at the firſt,<note place="margin">Pleſſis mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit. prog. 4 and 5.</note> the Pope only grew great as a Dioceſſan Biſhop in a great citty, haveing this only priviledge, that he was reckoned the Biſhop of the firſt ſea, and an Arch-Biſhop, Rome being the ſeate of the Empire, but there were then others that were reckoned Archbiſhops as well as hee, and governed theire ſeas as freely, as he did his: and ſo did many Biſhops alſo. It is well manifeſted by <hi>Hierome</hi> on the firſt of <hi>Titus</hi> and by many other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,<note place="margin">Bellar. de clericis lib. 1. c. 14.</note> and moderne writers cited by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina, as alſo by <hi>Pietro Scave Polano</hi> in his hiſtorie of the councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> that at firſt <hi>a preſbiter, and a Biſhop was one,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. of the Councell of Trent. pag. 220.331.332.591.</note> 
               <hi>and the ſame thing, that the Churches were gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the common counſailes of the presbiters,</hi> and how the juriſdiction, and power of Dioceſſan, and Provinciall Biſhops, crept into the church to withſtand diviſions; namely together with the Popes: and therefore to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:11723:35"/> their office is to defend his: which only differs in the exceſſe of power, and evill, and in ſupremacie, and univerſalitie: neither have they ſo much withſtood diviſions as increaſed them, for Pleſſis, and theſe other authors ſhew; by the bountie and favour of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, and his Princes, the Biſhop of Rome was made rich and great; but ſo were other Biſhops alſo. And as he began to have a tribunall, and courts, and cauſes; ſo did others alſo; and thence grew corruption upon corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, contention upon contention, appeale upon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale, diviſion upon diviſion. He grew to be reckoned a Patriarch: but the Biſhops of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och</hi> had the like priviledges given them; which ſoone after was alſo beſtowed on the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> becauſe it was become the Imperiall Cittie, as Rome had beene before. And though the <hi>Greek</hi> Biſhops would never acknowledge the Pope for their head, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there was no reaſon they ſhould, yet they muſt needes confeſſe that his riſing was theires. Their riſing, and greatnes was but an imitation of his: and ſo is that of the Archbiſhops of <hi>Toledo, Paris, Collen, Mentz, Trier, Canterburie, Yorke,</hi> and others, as alſo of the Biſhops of <hi>Angiers, London, Winchester,</hi> and <hi>Durham,</hi> and all others in the Chriſtian world, according to the greatnes of the Provinces, Cities, and Countries, whereof they obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the title and juriſdiction. The Pope was the Beaſt, and Antichriſt, before he got the title of univerſall Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, which made him theire head, &amp; the grand Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt: which hinders not but that before, and ſince, they by their office might be pettie Antichriſts. This would quickly appeare, if men would trie the ſpirits, trie the doctrines, trie the callings, and ſay. The calling of Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſan Biſhops, is it of God or of men? But if Biſhops may have their wills, you ſhall neither trie their callings,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:11723:36"/> nor their doctrines by the Scriptures. I wonder there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Princes and people of the reformed religion, ſhould have their doctrines and ceremonies in ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, becauſe of their perſons and offices, as if Gods ſpirit muſt needes be with them, more then with others when they ſhould rather thinke it to be leſſe with them, whoſe calling, and dominion is not of God, then with others, and that if their doctrines, traditions and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies agree not with the Scriptures, they cannot bee of God,<note place="margin">2 Ioh. 9. Ioh. 8.44. Acts. 14.23 Act. 20.17.28.</note> ſeing their authoritie, and office that impoſe them is not of God, but of the ſame ſpirit that ruleth in Antichriſt, they abide not in the government of Chriſt, but are enemies to it.</p>
            <p>For the Apoſtles <hi>ordained them Presbiters (that is El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders) in every Church by election,</hi> Paul ſaith to the Preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to the Elders. <hi>Take heede therefore unto your ſelves, and to all the flock over which the holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops</hi> (the word is the ſame that is uſed, 1. Tim. 3.1.2. and may be tranſlated a Biſhop, or an <hi>overſeer,</hi> even as in the Greeke a preſbiter is an Elder.) There were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of them over one flock. Therefore he ſaith. To the ſaints that are at <hi>Philippi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1.1. Tit. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>with the Biſhops and Deacons:</hi> the preſbiters were then the Biſhops, which is cleere by that, <hi>I left thee in Crete that thou ſhouldest ſet in order, the things that are wanting, and ordaine them</hi> Preſbiters in every Cittie (that is by election, according to Act. 14.23. Act. 1.23. Chap. 6.5. and 1. Tim. 4.14. as Beza well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it,<note place="margin">Verſ. 6.7.</note> in his Annotations on theſe places, and ſo Paul addeth) <hi>If any be blameleſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20. Phil. 1.</note> for <hi>a Biſhop</hi> (that is the preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aforenamed) <hi>must be blameleſſe;</hi> which is ſo cleere that <hi>Bellarm.</hi> that would faine denie it,<note place="margin">Bellarm. de Clericis. lib. 1. c. 14.</note> is forced to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſs that in all theſe three places the preſbiters are called Biſhops, and conſequently when Paul ſaieth, 1. Tim. 3. <hi>He that deſireth the office of a Biſhop, deſireth a good worke:</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:11723:36"/> that is the office of a Preſbiter; they were one, and the fame, as Hierom, and others cited by <hi>Bellarmin</hi> have af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed. Otherwiſe Paull would not have them paſſed, <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.</note> as he doth, from the office of a Biſhop to the office of a Deacon, but firſt from the office of a Biſhop, to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Preſbiter, and then to Deacons: but there he only ſpeakes of Biſhops, and Deacons, becauſe a Biſhop and a Preſbiter is one, and the ſame thing. It is true that <hi>Timothie</hi> was an Euangeliſt; which is greater then a Biſhop: but as he is called a Biſhop, that is, a preſbiter. <hi>Neglect not the gift that is in thee, which was give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie with the laying on of the hands of the Presbiterie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 4.14.</note> The preſbiters ye ſee were then the Biſhops that ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned preſbiters, that is Biſhops: and in that ſenſe, <hi>Titus</hi> a preſbiter, that is a Biſhop, was left to ordaine them preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters in every Cittie, that is Biſhops: but <hi>Titus</hi> was not a Biſhop of Biſhops: for if any of them were taken in a fault, the conſiſtorie of preſbiters were to looke to it, Acts, 20.28. So it is ſaid, againſt <hi>an Elder receive not an accuſation but before two, or three witneſses;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.19.</note> which is not to ſet one over the reſt, to make a Biſhop of Biſhops: but as if an Apoſtle ſhould write to a ſenator of <hi>Venice,</hi> againſt a Senator receive not an accuſation but before two or three witneſſes, which were to teach him, and all Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors their dutie. Chriſt ſaith of the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> 
               <hi>he ſhall not ſpeake of himſelf, he ſhall take of mine to ſhew unto you:</hi> to teach us that the holy Ghoſt bringeth no new doctrine or ordinance, that ſtands not with the old: for Chriſt changeth not; he is <hi>the ſame yesterday, and to day, &amp; for ever.</hi> But Paul ſaith of the Elders. <hi>The holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops;</hi> this ordinance therefore is unalterable.<note place="margin">Hebr. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Act. 20.</note> They ought to have the government, and the honour due to Elders, ſo Paul ſaith: <hi>Let the Elders that rule well be counted worthy of double honour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>eſpecially they who labour in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:11723:37"/> the word and doctrine.</hi> Next to the Apoſtles, and Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts the Elderſhip was the place of greateſt honour in the Church. None of the Apoſtles are called Biſhops, but Elders, they diſdained not the title, but reckoned it an honour.<note place="margin">2. Ioh. 1.</note> 
               <hi>The Elder to the Elect</hi> Ladie, and ſaint Pet. ſaith <hi>The Elders which are among you I exhort, who am alſo an Elder:</hi> the Greeke word ſignifies a fellow elder. The Apoſtles and Elders came together to conſider of this matter.<note place="margin">Act. 15.8.22.23.</note> The choſen menand decrees went out in all their names.</p>
            <p>Some object that Biſhops ſuccede the Apoſtles, and Preſbiters, the ſeaventie Diſciples. This is but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite. For Preſbiters were the Biſhops ordained of God, to ſucceede the Apoſtles. Chriſt ſaith to them. <hi>Loe I am with you alwaies to the end of the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28.20</note> That is in their ſucceſſors, ſuch as ſhould teach their doctrine, baptiſe, and governe according to his ordinance the <hi>Elderſhip,</hi> ſo they may have ſucceſſors; but not as they were Apoſtles, and over <hi>Elders,</hi> that is over Biſhops: for as <hi>Beza</hi> obſerveth the Apoſtles excerciſed no tirannous dominion,<note place="margin">Beza in Act 1.23.</note> or Lordſhip in the Church, but left them free voices, and free election, and to be an Apoſtle is to be ſent of God, with an immediate embaſſage to laie the foundation in practiſe, and ordinances, as Paul did, but the Embaſſage of Biſhops is mediate, they have theirs from the Apoſtles: neither can they lay another foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, nor ordaine new things, though they oft aſſume it, in ſome decrees, canons and ceremonies, as they did who eſtabliſhed dioceſſan Biſhops; to ſay they might doe it, or that their act was of the holy Ghoſt; it will follow that others might with like reaſon ordaine Archbiſhops, and Patriachs, and in the end a Pope over all; and that all theſe their acts were of the holy Ghoſt, but Biſhops, and Councells are not <hi>Maſterbuilders,</hi> as
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:11723:37"/> the Apoſtles were; for every one is willed, <hi>to take heed how he buildeth: for other foundation can no man lay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>then that is laid, which is Ieſus Christ.</hi> In this ſenſe each Apoſtle was a generall officer in all Churches, as Paul ſaith,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.28.</note> 
               <hi>He had the care of all Churches.</hi> But herein no Biſhop will call himſelfe his ſucceſſour: unles it be the Pope, who exalts himſelf above all that is called God.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.</note> Peter would not have any Elder to be a <hi>Lord ouer Gods heritage:</hi> much leſſe ouer other Elders. <hi>It ſhall not be ſo amongſt you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 20.25 Chap. 23.8</note> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>One is your Maiſter even Chriſt, and all ye are bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> There is no other Biſhop over theſe Biſhops, the Preſbyters, or Elders. He is the King of his Church, and the only <hi>chiefe</hi> Biſhop.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.25 Chap. 5.4.</note> It is a poore anſwer to all this to ſay this opinion was condemned for an hereſie in <hi>Aerius,</hi> ſeeing <hi>Chemnitius</hi> hath ſo well cleared him,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Chemnit. examen concil. Trid.</p>
                  <p>Bellarm. de Clericis, lib 1. cap. 14.</p>
               </note> and <hi>Medina</hi> alleadged by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> confeſſeth that ſaint <hi>Hierom was herein wholy of opinion with the Aerians, and not only S. Hierom,</hi> but likewiſe, <hi>Ambroſe, Augustin, Sedulius, Primaſius, Chryſostome, Theoderet, Oecumenius,</hi> and <hi>Theophilact.</hi> If theſe or other Fathers did yet hold dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſan Epiſcopacie to be lawfull, and neceſſarie; it may be anſwered, that otherwiſe the myſterie of iniquitie, could not have proceeded as it did: they lived not to ſee ſuch fruits of it, as wee have ſeene; it was not then come to the height of tyrannie, they therefore were more excuſable then wee can be: and therefore the cauſe is not bettered by this, that Engliſh Prelates hold with <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> and Rome in this point, ſeeing other reformed Churches finde it ſafer in this caſe, with <hi>Calvin,</hi> Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius, <hi>Beza,</hi> and others to cleave unto the Scriptures, and be reformed by them. In the Revelation,<note place="margin">Rev. 4.1.2 3.4. Cap. 5.6.</note> ſaint Iohn ſeeing the Church that was to be after him, ſaith, <hi>Behold a Throne was ſet in heaven: and round about the throne were foure and twentie Elders.</hi> And in the midſt of <hi>the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:11723:38"/> throne, and in the midst of the Elders</hi> ſtood Chriſt; to ſhew they belong to his government, as Dioceſſan Biſhops to that of Antichriſt; for note, he ſaith not Biſhops, but El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or Presbiters, leſt after it ſhould have bin taken for dioceſſan Biſhops. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Babylon</hi> is deſtroied, the <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> give thankes.<note place="margin">Rev. 19.4.</note> All this ſheweth that Chriſts Church ought to be governed by <hi>Elders,</hi> that ſo it was, and ſo it ſhalbe, this is the government of Chriſt, who is the king, and annointed to it. Now Dioceſſan and Provinciall Biſhops hinder this government, and are therein Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts; therefore that is true which <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid in his time,<note place="margin">1 Iohn. 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>Even now are many Antichrists.</hi> There is a veile upon ſome Proteſtants hearts, a curtaine of Church power before their eyes, that they cannot ſee this, and the infectious ſores and maladies that their power and ceremonies bring in and cover. I hope this curtaine is now ſo drawne, that Princes will for Chriſts ſake, lay it to heart, and take away their dominion and riches, which make them thus blinde and corrupt. For that is the end of this worke.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe it is cleare to all the wiſemen in the Chriſtian world, that as many great troubles have riſen in former times, about Prelates, as in England a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Becket, Stephen Langthon,</hi> and others: ſo of late all the warres and ſtirres in Germany, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts, have riſen from Biſhops, Ieſuits, and other Clergie men: they have made the Emperour and other Princes to kill, and drive the Proteſtants out of their Countries and livings. All the doe and hurliburly is raiſed to reſtore them to their Antichriſtian power in Biſhopricks, Deanaries, Cloiſters, and their revenues. Howſoever the fire began, theſe are the bellowes that blow it, and ſuch as miniſter the oyle and ſulphure that have nouriſhed and increaſed the flame. This ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the Clergy, that doth ſo much miſchiefe in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:11723:38"/> the Church &amp; Common wealth, is a helliſh flame, that cannot begin to go out, til Rome be burned, &amp; the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy reformed by the Scriptures. True peace &amp; unity there can be none, till their dominion, riches, &amp; authority be taken away, and they reduced to the truth of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Looke into England, and ſee if theſe vices, and pride in the Clergy, have not beene cauſe of all the diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and diſgraces of that Country. The late Duke knew well that he could not ſtand, practiſe, and prevaile, without their countenance and authority: to maintaine their greatneſſe, ſave their honour and power entire, keepe their practices, and corruptions in matter of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, from being queſtioned and reformed, Parliaments muſt bee diſturbed, yea cruſhed and diſſolved, and, as men ſay, the moſt ſincere lovers of juſtice and piety in that high Court, muſt be diſgraced, accuſed, and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, for diſcovering the practices of the Arminian, Popiſh, or Spaniſh factions; and ſuch flatteries, and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of the Clergy, as appeare in Pulpit, print, and practice. The Biſhops ſee all this, and know that by all theſe meanes, their power and authority is encreaſed, as that of the Church of Rome, and other popiſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops was by the like.</p>
            <p>But they that by theſe meanes cheriſh ſuch factions, countenance or ſuffer Arminian Bookes, and practices to paſſe, and doe little againſt the Popiſh, are not ſo cold in defending that tradition of theirs, or rather of the Papiſts, that Dioceſſan Biſhops, and their authority in things called indifferent, are of God; but to ſhew that like the Papiſts they are more jealous, ſenſible, and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of any thing done againſt theſe, then againſt thoſe that are done againſt the kingdome, word, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God, they are ever watchfull, carefull, and zealous, to hinder all bookes and diſcoveries that are
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:11723:39"/> againſt any of their traditions and ceremonies; not one muſt be ſuffered to be ſeene that hath any proofe for the Elderſhip, or againſt the Hierarchy: pretending ſtill they are hereticall, and dangerous, which is but a Popiſh tricke, and a mockery, while in the meane thoſe of the Arminians are ſuffered to paſſe, and the popiſh are not ſo ſeverely ſuppreſſed, though hereticall, and very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to the ſoule.</p>
            <p>In the hiſtory of the Councell of Trent it is ſhewed that <hi>In the Church of Martyrs there was no eccleſiaſticall prohibition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 472.</note> 
               <hi>though ſome godly men made conſcience of read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bad bookes for three reaſons of Gods law to avoid the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion of evill: not to expoſe ones ſelfe to temptation, without neceſsity or profit: and not to ſpend time vainly. About the yeare</hi> 400. <hi>a Councell in Carthage did forbid to reade the bookes of the Gentiles, but allowed them to reade the bookes of the heretickes: the decree whereof is among the Canons col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by Gratian. And this was the firſt prohibition by way of Canon. The bookes of heretickes, containing doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by Councels, were often forbid by the Emperours, as by Constantine thoſe of the Arrians, by Arcadius thoſe of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemius and Maniches, by Theodoſius thoſe of Neſtorius, by Martianus thoſe of the Euticheans. It ſufficed the Councels and Biſhops to ſhew what bookes did containe damned or apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphall doctrine. So did Gelaſius in the yeare</hi> 494. <hi>and went no further, leaving it to the conſcience of every one to avoid, or reade them to a good end. After the yeare</hi> 800. <hi>the Popes of Rome, as they aſſumed a great part of the politicke govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo they cauſed the bookes of thoſe authors they did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne, to be burned, and forbad the reading of them. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding one ſhall finde but few bookes forbid in that ſort untill this age. Martin the</hi> 5. <hi>doth in a Bull excommunicate all the ſects of heretickes, eſpecially Wicleifists, and Huſsites, not mentioning thoſe who reade their bookes, though many of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:11723:39"/> them went about. Leo</hi> 10. <hi>condemning Luther, did withall forbid all his bookes upon paine of excommunication. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the following Popes, and the Councell of Trent did the like for all the bookes of the Reformiſts. In the yeare</hi> 1558. <hi>the King of Spaine made a law, that the Catalogue of bookes prohibited by the Inquiſition ſhould be printed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This diſcourſe being larger in the Author, ſheweth that it is a ſhame for the Engliſh Biſhops to follow their novell and popiſh courſe againſt them that prove the Elderſhip to be Gods ordinance; and argues a bad cauſe in the Prelates, which they dare not ſuffer to be diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor the bookes againſt it to bee ſeene, though they hold the things to be indifferent, and of a poſitive law: and that while they ſuffer thoſe of the Arminians, and in the mean hinder thoſe that confute them, this argues plaine policy, and Trent tyranny, for all this is done at their inſtance.</p>
            <p>It is pretended, that neither this knowledge of the Elderſhip, nor that which convinceth the Arminian te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, are needfull in a Chriſtian; which is but a moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery, while they would that men ſhould know that there ought to be Biſhops, and that they ſhould bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, though they prohibit teaching of the revealed truth of God, touching his free grace, in election, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, mans free will, and the like; and in the meane ſuffer the contrary doctrine to paſs in Arminian books. For while they ſay, theſe things are too high for the people, let them learne eaſier, and bee taught to pray, &amp;c. they are willingly ignorant, that by ſuch trickes the Papiſts at firſt put off the truth of God, and in time eſtabliſhed their owne errors in matter of juſtification, tranſubſtantiation, merits, and the like; that if this be granted, the like art may after be uſed in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and thence others may in time ſay, Chriſt is given
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:11723:40"/> and eaten in the Sacrament, Miniſters doe binde and looſe, Chriſtians are juſtified, it is ſufficient to beleeve theſe things, and not to know how, they are high mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, therefore the meane knowledge is beſt: and ſo by degrees in other points. Which being granted, after this ſecond ſtep to ignorance, errour, and poperie, there would follow a third, that the Prelates would bee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted in them, ſet out corrupt gloſſes, multiply Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and then you muſt beleeve as the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves, that is, as they beleeve, or bee accounted a ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticke, and in the end an hereticke.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe, that if Papiſts and Arminians did not ſtrive to corrupt men in theſe points, ſuch exact confutations of them, and knowledge of the truth in them, might ſeem leſſe neceſſary; and in ſome ſort to forbid it, were not plain trechery, as now it is counted in the Prelates; That there ought to bee a good order in mens know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; not to minde nothing elſe but theſe points, nor to beginne with them, and then come to learne the firſt principles of the Oracles of God: but they being firſt learned which touch a mans particular ſalvation, then to come to thoſe which touch the ſalvation and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Church, and conſequently of every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſoule in it, the knowledge of the like being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in the Revelation,<note place="margin">Rev. 1.3.</note> that we may pray to God for a reformation; leſt the Prelates reigning thus, the faith come to be corrupted, and diſeſteemed, traditions, errour, and will-worſhip advanced, as in the Church of Rome: who by keeping Princes and people in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the matter of their Hierarchie, and traditions, and pretending divers points were too high for pariſh pulpits, and laicks, brought them to that height of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety and errour wherein they are. Whence we may ſee, that leſt the like evils come on us, as they begin,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:11723:40"/> the knowledge of Gods ordinances in matters of the <hi>Elderſhip,</hi> and things againſt the Hierarchie and traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is more neceſſary in every underſtanding man, then one would thinke at the firſt ſight. It concerneth the faith it ſelfe, and the keeping of it uncorrupt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe without it the Church is ſure to be kept in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, many points of faith loſt or changed, as in the Church of Rome: and ſo many ſoules corrupted and perverted to perdition. For they know that if Princes and people know it not, the King and Parliament can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come to know it, much leſſe to reforme it; and by all this we ſee plainly that greater corruptions will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitably follow, and the Prelates will come to that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, that men ſhall not dare to diſcover them.</p>
            <p>When the light of the Goſpell did but begin to bee reſtored, and errours by it to be diſcovered, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Ambaſſadors came in his name to the Legates in Trent, deſiring 20. points of reformation, of which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe. That no ſcandalous diſpenſations may bee granted hereafter.<note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent, pag, 513.</note> That plurality of benefices may bee taken away, and Schooles erected in Cathedrall and Collegiat Churches. That every Eccleſiaſticall mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie be exerciſed freely, and that rich benefices with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cure, may be incorporated to thoſe that have cure, and ſmall revenue. That the Canons againſt Simonie may be revived. That the Eccleſiaſticall conſtitutions be abridged, the ſuperfluity cut off, and not made equall to the obligations of the law of God. That excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication be not uſed but for mortall ſinne, or notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous irregularity. That divine ſervice be ſo ſaid, as that it may be underſtood by him that ſaith it, and by him that heareth it. That a way bee found not to chaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way bad pariſh Prieſts, becauſe that is eaſie, but to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute better. I omit others of allowing mariage to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:11723:41"/> Prieſts, and the cup to ſome nations.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 651.</note>The French Ambaſſadours had the like. The Prieſts ſhould not be ordained before they were old, and had a good teſtimony of the people, that they had lived well. That a Prieſt ſhould not be ordained before hee had a benefice, or miniſtery, according to the Councell of Chalcedon, at which time a preſbyterall title with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an office was not heard of. That the due function ſhould be reſtored to Deacons, and other holy orders, and they may not ſeeme to beare names, and for cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony onely. That the Prieſts, and other Eccleſiaſticall Miniſters, ſhould attend to their vocation, not medling in any office but in the divine Miniſtery. That Biſhops, Pariſh Prieſts, and other Eccleſiaſtickes, unable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their charge, ſhall receive coadjutors, or leave their benefices. That no man ſhall have more then one benefice, taking away the differences of the quality of the perſons, and of benefices compatible, and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible, a new diviſion not heard of in the ancient de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees. That he that hath two or more, ſhall retaine that onely which hee ſhall chooſe, within a ſhort time, or ſhall incurre the penalty of the ancient Canons. That the mandates of proviſion, expectations, regreſſions, reſignations in confidence to be revoked, and baniſhed out of the Church, as contrary to the decrees. If either the people or Princes of England, ſhould make theſe or the like to the Parliament, or Convocation of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, they ſhould preſently be hiſſed out for Puritans, as the Cardinals called thoſe <hi>Vltramontan</hi> Biſhops hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, that held reſidency to be <hi>ex jure divino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pa. 501.</note>Some thinke, if there were better Biſhops all would be well enough. Indeed it could not bee ſo bad; but well it could never be: becauſe Dioceſſan Biſhops are not ordained of God, they are no branches of Gode
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:11723:41"/> engrafting, their office hath no root in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> the true Vine, who is the Word: ſuch officers and offices as the Father hath planted in him, bring forth fruit unto him: He is the <hi>doore,</hi> by which all true Shepheards enter; he that <hi>climbeth up another way</hi> (be it by a poſitive law,<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.1.</note> or otherwiſe) <hi>the ſame is a theefe, and a robber,</hi> and brings forth ſuch fruits as dioceſſan Epiſcopacy hath. Some Biſhops there are indeed that have ſhewed themſelves againſt the Arminians, and Papiſts, and to be lovers of preaching, and ſound doctrine; even as Chriſt had ſome witneſſes or friends among the Rulers and Phariſes; but theſe have beene ſoone quailed, and kept out of grace in the Court; howſoever they are great friends of the hierarchy, and enemies of the Elderſhip, and true refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and ſo affected to thoſe great places, that they are blinde on that ſide; and in that reſpect ſo againſt the kingdome of God, that the devill and the Ieſuits know well enough that they are herein more helpers to the Romiſh religion, then hinderers, becauſe they uphold the reputation of dioceſſan Biſhops, and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, with the moſt religious ſort of conformiſts, and ſo doe but hold way for worſe ſucceſſors. It is ſtrange that wiſe men, and ſome both conſcionable and well ſeene in Divinity, ſhould ſuffer themſelves to be ſo ſeduced in this point, as to thinke dioceſſan and provinciall Epiſcopacy lawfull and neceſſary. 1. Becauſe they ſee it was very anciently ordained and exerciſed by good men, and that the received cuſtome was confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Nicene Councell: whereas they ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſider, that it was not in the Church of Martyrs, as it is now; the Biſhops then differed little from Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters in pompe and authority, and did not reigne over them as now: that though thoſe Fathers might thinke to doe good in ordaining it; unleſſe they had erred
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:11723:42"/> therein, and namely in taking ſo much on them, and yet had ſeemed to doe it as a thing neceſſary and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, it had not beene poſſible that the myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity ſhould have wrought ſo ſoone, and that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, who was to be a Biſhop, and to ſit in the Temple of God, ſhould have found meanes, and ſtep after ſtep to riſe to his greatneſſe out of that ordinance, as was ſhewed he did:<note place="margin">In an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the hiſtory of the Counc. of Trent.</note> That ſome evill things have beene or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in Councels very ancient, as Biſhop Iewed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſteth: that this proved ſuch in ſhort time: that therefore it is not good to thinke of reducing dioceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan Biſhops to their firſt eſtate, but rather of taking them away, becauſe ſuch trees muſt needs bring forth ſuch fruit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe many zealous and well affected men have beene, and ſome now are dioceſſan Biſhops. I anſwer, have they not read that ſome zealous Prieſts &amp; Biſhops have come to be Pope? as of old <hi>Gregory</hi> 1. and divers others: and of late <hi>Adrian</hi> 6. reckoned holy men: which makes their papall calling never a whit more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable or lawfull: no more doth it in thoſe Engliſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, that otherwiſe are ſound in religion. For they ſtanding ſo ſtoutly for hierarchy, traditions, and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which are Romiſh, and have their ſtrength from Romiſh ambition, power, and uſurpation, even in theſe beſt Biſhops, the tree is knowne by his fruit; and in this reſpect, they are all drunke with the wine of her fornication, though ſome more, ſome leſſe. For they that have otherwiſe beene good Preachers, are the worſe when they come to be Biſhops, or to affect ſuch places: they make them ſo ceremonious, and zealous of the hierarchy, canons, ſervice, and ceremonies, that they ſticke not to preach them; and ſo loth to diſpleaſe Courtiers, that they are the leſſe againſt Popery, and the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:11723:42"/> more plaine enemies of ſuch true Proteſtants, as ſeeke the Elderſhip and right reformation: whom they will not permit to write or ſpeake, much leſſe to preach the truth of God in thoſe points, but ſcoffe, mocke, puniſh, impriſon and ſilence them, keeping the Princes by theſe and all the ſhifts they can, in ignorance in this point, as the Papiſts doe theirs in this point and in others. The ancient Fathers did not thus, they were not ſuch Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</p>
            <p>Thus the whole counſaile of God is not ſuffered to be preached in England, ſhall I ſay in theſe points of the elderſhip, hierarchy, and ſervice onely? wherein a man is not ſo much as ſuffered to diſtinguiſh betweene a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificer, and a Preſbyter, or Prieſt, as all Miniſters are called? No, a myſtery of iniquity cannot reſt in two or three evils: but thoſe obſtinately defended by men, God gives them over to greater blindneſſe and errour. So was it in the Church of Rome, and ſo hath it beene in England, where at firſt it was indeed ſaid, why ſhould men ſtumble ſo much at Biſhops and ceremonies, ſo long as the Goſpell may be freely preached in all other things, and no Miniſter hindred in them? but now it is come to another evill, the bondage and limitations are more increaſed. For the Clergy, and eſpecially the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, have not onely temporiſed with the <hi>Duke,</hi> and other hiſpaniolized and popiſh agents and practiſers; but even for their favour let in Arminianiſme, neither op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it themſelves, nor ſuffering others that would; but becauſe light remedies alwayes cheriſh an evil, they got the King to prohibite diſputes on both ſides, not to hinder Arminianiſme, (for the bookes of Doctor <hi>Iackſon</hi> and others, were ſuffered to come out after that) but others from confuting it in their diſputations, books, and ſermons; and in ſtead of the Scriptures to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:11723:43"/> make the Articles the <hi>Rule,</hi> and them the interpreters of them, who have not onely protected the <hi>Appealer,</hi> Doctor <hi>Iackſon,</hi> Doctor <hi>Couſens,</hi> and ſome others that ſavour of Arminianiſme and Popery, hindred the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and others from convincing them of errour, and ſo emboldned others to broach worſe errours in flattery of mighty favourites, helped to get Parliaments diſſolved, wherein men had ſome hope of remedy: but have themſelves preached ſome paſſages ſavouring of Romiſh and Trent corruption, ſeeming to approve the vulgar edition, that the Sacraments confer grace <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> and to tye the underſtanding of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to the interpretation of the Fathers, to make the beſt of moderne Divines, little regarded. In theſe and the like, they being powerfull in Court, cannot want followers and flatterers; and therefore men of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſay they are not ſo well read in the Rules of piety, as in thoſe of policy, uſed againſt the deſired re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in the time of <hi>Luther,</hi> which being ſet forth in the hiſtory of the Councell of Trent, though it an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the Papiſts, in regard it diſcovereth a world of their various diſſimulations, cunning ſhifts and devices, yet it pleaſeth them in this, that they ſerve to teach the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and Arminians how to fruſtrate and delude all the faireſt proofes and attempts of their adverſaries. And becauſe ſome have written to diſcover the errours, practices, and dangers, they have not onely put all they could catch in the high Commiſſion, but leſt ſuch ſhould get out, and themſelves be any way hindred or diſcovered in ſuch proceedings, they have obtained authority, that if any writer, Printer, or Book-ſeller, come with a prohibition, he ſhall be preſently cenſured. Some will ſay, this is but reaſon. I anwſer, true, if their hierarchie and practices were according to Gods word,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:11723:43"/> and they ſeditious and hereticall that they trouble: but being as it is, and this power ſeldome or never exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt any but ſuch as ſtand for Gods truth againſt Arminians, popiſh practiſers and defenders of the hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy, they abuſe the King and Councell, in getting them to be their protectors, and are themſelves blinde and Antichriſtian tyrants. Such as in ſtead of follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the rules of the Goſpell ſeeme rather to encline to that of Paul 4. who ſet on foot the Inquiſition,<note place="margin">Hiſt. of the Councell of Trent. pag. 405. &amp; 409.</note> which he ſaid was the principall ſecret and myſtery of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, the true <hi>Ramme</hi> to beat down hereſie, and defend the Apoſtolike ſea, by advancing another, which like it ſhall prevaile by power and terrour in ſtead of good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, namely the high Commiſſion Court.</p>
            <p>The Councellors of the Parliament of Paris, ſeeing the Articles of reformation publiſhed in the Councell of Trent, oppoſed, ſaying, the Eccleſiaſticall authority was enlarged beyond its bounds, with the wrong and diminution of the temporall, by giving power to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to proceed to pecuniary mulcts, and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the laity; whereas no authority was given by Chriſt to his Miniſters, but meere and pure ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: that when the Clergy was made a member of the policy, the Princes did by favour allow the Biſhops to puniſh inferiour Clergy men with temporall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that diſcipline might be obſerved amongſt them, but to uſe ſuch kinde of puniſhment againſt the laickes, they had neither from the law of God, nor of man, but by uſurpation onely. All which ſheweth, that dioceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan Biſhops are great impoſtors, though the Pope bee indeed the grand impoſtor. And let men be ſure, that as they and their hierarchy are more and more defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo will their power encreaſe, and grow more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, blinde, erroneous, and Antichriſtian, as that of the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:11723:44"/> Church of Rome did; their <hi>feare</hi> towards God being in theſe things taught by the <hi>precepts of men,</hi> the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of them and their ſupporters, muſt needs <hi>decay</hi> and periſh, to the extreame danger of the Church and Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>By all which may bee ſeene, that the kingdome of God, in the true, free, and full power of the word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, is incompatible with the hierarchy; they cannot ſtand together, but the maintenance of the one is the breaking of the bands of the other, and of the true peace and happineſſe of the Church and State; and that therefore there is neceſſity of a reformation in the Church, and reſtoring the ordinances of God to that forme, which not any humane, but his divine wiſdome ordained.</p>
            <p>Some have pretended, that it is good policy to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Hierarchy; for ſay they, <hi>no Biſhop, no King;</hi> there muſt be <hi>order</hi> in the Church, and Biſhops are they that preſerve it. This is that bulwark which they uſed to beat off all juſt complaints, and ſave themſelves, their cauſe, their friends and followers, ſuch as the <hi>Duke,</hi> the <hi>Appealer,</hi> and <hi>Couſens,</hi> from the parliamentary power. Cruſhed and diſſolved it muſt be, rather then ſuch a one or his trechery be brought to triall; though they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by make ſuch the more bold to attempt the like or worſe evills, overthrow the power and uſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that confirmed their hierarchy, (a requitall not ſo ſtrange in them, as juſt with God) and ſo alienate the heart of the King from his ſubjects, and the ſubjects from the King, though they know, <hi>a kingdome divided in it felfe cannot ſtand;</hi> that having their hearts hee is ſtrong, and a King indeed; that otherwiſe hee cannot well ſubſiſt, as a King ſhould, nor be ſupplied with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and men: but muſt bee forced to make peace with
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:11723:44"/> the enemies of religion on the harder conditions; and home-bred Papiſts and Arminians would thereby grow the bolder, to encreaſe their religions and parties; the <hi>Palatinate</hi> could not well be recovered, but the enemy muſt needs be made the more abſolute and reſolute, to root out our religion and brethren in forraigne parts, and at laſt, ſeeing diviſion in England, to venture thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to endanger the Church and Commonweale, the Kingdome, and all. Wherein what have the Prelates ſhewed leſſe, then that they had rather all theſe ſhould be ſhaken and endangered, then their hierarchy; or then one proud <hi>Appealer,</hi> one popiſh <hi>Couſens</hi> ſhould be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned in diſparagement thereof. For theſe evils could not have beene effected againſt ſo many endeavours of Parliaments, without the helpe of their religious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, nor paſſed without the cloake of their Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall gravity. And leſt things ſhould bee diſcovered or reproved, beſides their diligence in ſuppreſſing of bookes, they have got the Court and Croſſe ſupplied with Preachers for their owne turne, yea cauſed ſome mens ſermons to be peruſed beforehand, according to the policy uſed in the third convocation of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent, pag. 468.</note> where the Biſhop of <hi>Modena</hi> was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to peruſe every ſermon, and whatſoever elſe was to be delivered in publike.</p>
            <p>By all which, he that will may ſee, that as it was ever in the hierarchy, ſo hath it beene, is, and will be in this, the more Biſhop and hierarchy, the leſſe King, the leſſe good order in Church and Commonwealth. For they have beene in effect the Kings, nothing muſt bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, or heard againſt them, or ſuch friends of theirs, as the Duke, and others: but ſtill they pretend that theſe complaints are not ſo much againſt them, as againſt the Kings government and prerogative: which is a meere
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:11723:45"/> trick and colour to engage the King in their cauſe, and ſo to ſave them, their friends and practices from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to triall: and ſo in concluſion it comes to be their prerogative that muſt not bee touched by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor indeed by the word of God. Is not this to bring all out of order? And which makes the evill ſeeme the more incurable, no man dares manifeſt ſo much, ſo able are they to undoe him. Which is a power the devill hath purchaſed them, that they and others may boldly proceed to propagate other errours, and doe what evill they liſt without controule, like the Church of Rome; and that to maintaine them, their pontificall greatneſſe, their Pallaces and Coaches, religion may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in their power, be made a leaden rule for them to turne which way they liſt, the trueſt lovers of Truth oppreſſed, the kingdome of God invaded and uſurped, and the whole Chriſtian world diſturbed and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</p>
            <p>Are not men aſhamed, that living in the light of the Goſpel, the love of Chriſt conſtraines them not to be againſt theſe men, but that they ſhould nevertheleſſe ſuffer themſelves to be made the friends and protectors of them and their hierarchy, and to thinke that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they either ſerve God, or the King and State, as they ought? For firſt that their hierarchy is againſt the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, if enough hath not beene ſaid, this may be added; that while the office of Dioceſſan Biſhops is falſly held to be <hi>ex jure divino,</hi> as we have proved, Gods ordinances and officers being rejected, the Church is governed by their greateſt adverſaries: who alſo having gotten the ruling and deſciſſive voices in Councels, (which ſhould rather belong to thoſe true Biſhops and Paſtors the Preſbyters) make their owne opinions and errours of Biſhops and traditions to bee received for
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:11723:45"/> matters of faith, as in the Councel of Trent. For though ſome hold that it is no matter of faith, but rather indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, and at the pleaſure of Kings, whether they or <hi>Elders</hi> ſhould governe the Church; yet it is of no leſſe conſequence; becauſe even in England they make their Articles to bee received, and in a wreſted or doubtfull ſenſe to be a ſure <hi>Rule,</hi> and ſo matters of faith, as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves interpret them; yea this to be granted, that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their adherents, aſſembled in Convocation, as the Church repreſentative: which if it make other Articles more unſound or ſavouring of Arminianiſme, or other errour, will thinke they ſhould bee received, eſpecially in matters of their authority: for who can hinder it, or dare ſay they have not power to decide what is the faith? when indeed ſeeing the inſtitution of Dioceſſan Biſhops is of a poſitive law, and not <hi>de jure divino,</hi> men ſhould rather conſider the conſequences: which were very aptly ſet forth in the Councell of Trent,<note place="margin">Hiſt. of the Councell of Trent. pag. 608.</note> where the Papalins maintaining that the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and juriſdiction of Biſhops were not <hi>de jure di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino,</hi> but that Biſhops had their juriſdiction from the Pope, and that hee onely had received inſtitution and juriſdiction from Chriſt in the perſon of <hi>Peter;</hi> the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Segna</hi> replyed, That if they have it not from Chriſt, neither can the Councell have any from him, which conſiſteth of Biſhops, that if Biſhops are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by Chriſt, the authority of them is altogether humane, and he that heareth it ſpoken, that Biſhops are not inſtituted by Chriſt, muſt needs thinke that this Synod is a congregation of prophane men, in which Chriſt doth not preſide, but a power received precarily from men, and it would be a great illuſion generally of all Chriſtendome to propoſe it, not onely as the beſt, but as the onely and neceſſary meanes to decide con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:11723:46"/> That hee would never have come to the Councell, if he had not beleeved that Chriſt had beene in the midſt of it; that if any Biſhop ſhould beleeve and thinke his authority to bee humane, it had beene great boldneſſe in him to denounce, in the former difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, anathematiſmes, and not rather refer all to him, who had greater authority.</p>
            <p>Now howſoever the opinion of the <hi>Papalins</hi> that the Pope is the onely Biſhop <hi>jure divino,</hi> and that others ought to have inſtitution from him, is moſt erroneous; yet ſeeing it is certaine that the inſtitution and juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of dioceſſan Biſhops are not from Chriſt, but of a poſitive law, all thoſe conſequences alledged by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Segna</hi> doe follow thereupon; and thoſe alſo which the Biſhop of Paris added againſt the tenet of <hi>Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nez</hi> Generall of the Ieſuites, who exceeded in maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cauſe againſt the Biſhops:<note place="margin">Pag. 614.</note> That in ſtead of a ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall kingdome (for ſo the Church is called) it maketh it not a kingdome, but a temporall tyranny; that it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth from the Church the title of the Spouſe of Chriſt, and maketh it a ſervant, proſtituted to man: whence it followes, that the Engliſh Hierarchy, having no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from Chriſt, is a temporall tyranny, and the Spouſe of Chriſt is made a ſervant, and ſubjected to it. It is true, that where two or three are gathered together in Chriſts name, there is he in the midſt: but to bee truly gathered together in his name, requireth that their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice be <hi>de jure divino,</hi> and they hare power from him to aſſemble and handle ſuch matters: this he never gave to dioceſſan Biſhops; for he never ordained them: they are but intruders, uſurping that which by Gods inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion belonged to Paſtors that are Preſbyters. With the Trent Fathers they pretend right by that place: <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, and to all the flocke over which the Holy Ghoſt
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:11723:46"/> hath made you Biſhops, to feed the Church of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.28</note> which is ſpoken to Preſbyters, and yet by uſurping theſe letters patents of the Preſbyters, dioceſſan Biſhops take the charge from them, exclude the Preſbyters, to whom they were granted, and what worſe is, reigne over them as over their ſubjects, who muſt not preach any thing that diſlikes them. That election is of Gods free grace, regeneration and converſion of his power, and not of mans free will; that men doe beleeve and perſevere, becauſe they were predeſtinated, though they be plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught in the Scripture, yet they will not have them nor the like points cleared by Preachers in Pulpit nor Print, nor by Divines in the Vniverſities, no not in a time when Papiſts &amp; Arminians corrupt men in them; but they muſt be left to them the Fathers and Rulers: as if dioceſſan Biſhops, never ordained of God, being many of them Courtiers, ſwolne with ambition, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on the intereſts of favourites, ſuch as the Duke, parties in ſuch factions, corrupted with flatteries, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting againſt the endeavours of Parliaments, daily bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied at the Councell table, in the Star chamber, or high Commiſſion Court, ſhould better know how to cleere and determine theſe and other high points, then Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers that ſtudy nothing elſe but Divinity, and are not led by ſuch particular intereſts. There is no man that hath but an indifferent judgement, and any ſparke of true love to Gods Kingdome, but will ſay, it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that theſe men, or their flatterers, ſhould bee fit Iudges, or give juſt lawes to men in ſuch caſes: yet they governe all in Synods, and elſewhere; and if they have but colourable pretences like the Papiſts, who doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt or queſtion them? Theſe are they that ruling all, and having many things in their gift, are ſure to be flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and followed in Court Synods, and Vniverſities:
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:11723:47"/> and if, as the Appealer doth, they can but alledge the opinion of Biſhop <hi>Bancraft,</hi> or any ſuch politician Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late like themſelves, they care for no better authority. Onely ſtrengthned by the ſecular arme, they know how to prevaile by power.</p>
            <p>All which conſidered, it is no marvell that they have decreed ſo many things to ſo little profit, yea to ſo great damage to the Church and kingdome of God. And all true Chriſtians are the rather to take heed of them and their decrees, and not to ſay, it is either neceſſary to have Biſhops, or a thing indifferent, ſeeing they ſo much endanger the faith, and that in theſe reſpects it greatly concernes the faith and all the faithfull to have their government aboliſhed, and the Elderſhip reſtored, leſt by them, as by the Biſhops in the Church of Rome, religion come to be corrupted.</p>
            <p>It will be objected, the moſt ancient Councels were governed by Biſhops. I anſwer, that otherwiſe Popiſh errours could not have beene eſtabliſhed, nor ſo long maintained againſt the truth; that at firſt Preſbyters had their voices in them, that Biſhops of old differed little from Preſbyters, had paſtorall charges, and were not like ours; but onely began to decline: and therefore I wonder not that <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſo long ſince obſerved that there came little good, yea much hurt of them, and that contentions have alwayes beene encreaſed by the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopall aſſemblies: as alſo Biſhop Iewel proves in many particulars.<note place="margin">In an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the hiſtory of the Counc. of Trent.</note> I wonder not if in our dayes ſome Biſhops are learned, affect ſome good things, make ſome good bookes, and tollerable conſtitutions. For ſome of them have beene great Divines, Paſtors, and of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in many things: but might not a man have found the like in ſome of the <hi>Sadduces, Heredians, Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piſts,</hi> and other heretikes? that is, take
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:11723:47"/> them out of their hereſies, in ſuch things as they hold common with other Iewes or Chriſtians? yet many things determined by them were dangerous; ſo muſt it needs be in the dioceſſan Biſhops of England, who are of a humane law, and heretikes in matter of the Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, if not Arminians. Therefore in this cauſe that may be ſaid of them which <hi>Paul</hi> 4. ſaid of the Biſhops of his time, that it was a vanity to aſſemble 60.<note place="margin">Pa. 339.</note> Biſhops of the leaſt able, and 40. Doctors of the moſt inſufficient, as was twice done already in Trent, and to beleeve that, by thoſe, things could bee well regulated; All which conſidered, who can thinke that the Hierarchy, or any Synod of Engliſh Biſhops, can be for the ſervice of God? In the meane the Churches, or at leaſt many thouſands in them, in their practice, receive the hierarchy, cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and traditions, <hi>Pari pietatis affectu, ac reverentiae,</hi> with like affection of piety and reverence, as the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word of God, and many with greater.</p>
            <p>There are foure pillars that uphold the Hierarchy. 1. Traditions and ceremonies. 2. Spirituall ignorance and blinde devotion in the Nobility and Laity. For that makes them take it for granted, that Biſhops and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their traditions are <hi>de jure divino:</hi> hence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes a 3. Riches and authority; and from theſe a 4. reciprocall reſolution &amp; combination with ſuch Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as the Duke and his confederates, ſo to maintaine each others cauſe againſt al accuſers, as if they were one, and they each others Advocates. And as a branch of this the ſevere ſuppreſſion of all bookes and complaints that diſcover their errors or practices. There is no need to prove further that the three laſt are againſt the ſervice of God, it will ſuffice to ſhew that they are againſt the ſervice of the King and State. But firſt of ceremonies and traditions received in the Church of England.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:11723:48"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent, pag. 259.</note>It is remarkable, that when ſome German Proteſtants for feare received thoſe appointed in the <hi>Interim,</hi> ſaying after they were indifferent: <hi>Others whom neceſsity had not compelled, ſaid it was true, that indifferent things concerne not ſalvation: yet, by meanes of them, pernicious things are brought in; and going on, they framed this generall conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, That ceremonies and rites, though by nature indifferent, doe then become bad, when he that uſeth them hath an opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that they are good or neceſſary.</hi> Which hath beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of them in England, and that generally they are men popiſh, neutrall, or of leaſt ſincerity, that ſtand moſt for them, as for the beſt meanes to uphold the hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy, becauſe they know that rule to be true, <hi>No cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, no Biſhop:</hi> which (as it ſeemes) is the reaſon that the Biſhops looke to little elſe, though that bee to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that they ſerve for nothing but to uphold their owne traditions and ceremonies: wherein they are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry zealous, like the Trent Biſhops, that anathematized them that ſay <hi>that the ceremonies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pa. 574.</note> 
               <hi>vestments, or externall ſignes uſed in the Maſſe, are rather incitements to ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pa. 548.</note> 
               <hi>then offices of piety.</hi> Where, if by <hi>ungodlineſſe</hi> you underſtand ſuperſtition and ignorance, the Trent cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is extreame harſh: the rather becauſe Antonius of Veltelina, a Dominican, had proved unto them, that the Rite of Rome had beene received to gratifie the Pope, but not in all places: and by a booke (called <hi>Ordo Romanus</hi>) that it hath had great alterations, not onely in ancient times, but even in the latter ages alſo, that the Roman Rite, obſerved within 300. yeares, is not that which is now obſerved by the Prieſts in that City. For the veſtments, veſſels, and other ornaments of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Altars, it appeareth not by bookes onely, but by ſtatues and pictures, that they are ſo changed, that if the Ancients ſhould returne into the world, they could
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:11723:48"/> not know them. Therefore he concluded, that to bind all to approve the Rites, which the Church of Rome uſed, might be reprehended, as a condemnation of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, and of the uſe of other Churches. His diſcourſe diſpleaſed, but the Biſhop of the five Churches juſtified him. If Engliſh Biſhops would but with the Friar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the conſequences that follow their inforcing of their Rites, they would not bee ſo extreame in them. And indeed in thoſe wherein they differ from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, they doe but mocke the Chriſtian world, while with the Papiſts they hold that they ought to be ſo ſtrictly received and reverenced, and yet abrogate others more neceſſary:<note place="margin">Pag. 163.</note> ſeeing as one ſaith of the Papiſts, <hi>they grant not to the people the election of the Minister, which certainly was an Apostolicall institution, continued more then eight hundred yeares:</hi> but deny it to them, with as good right, as the Papiſts doe both that and the uſe of the cup, which had beene continued as long.</p>
            <p>It is a ſeemly thing to ſee the Temples where Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians uſe to meet, in good repaire, frequented with grave, devout, humble, and religious behaviour, in the worſhip of God, the table covered with cleane linnen, when the Sacrament is adminiſtred, the cup decent and not of the baſeſt metall. But theſe and the like things are the more acceptable to God, when the Church is not ſpoiled of her better ornaments, diligent preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and hearing, ſoundneſſe in the faith, knowledge, zeale, and holineſſe of life. For if the Temples be never ſo glorious in ſtructure, the table of the fineſt wood and workmanſhip, the cup of gold, the Miniſters in glorious veſtments, the ſervice full of grave and devout ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and all things elſe in the moſt plauſible manner for outward ornament, God is but mocked for all theſe,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:11723:49"/> if thoſe better ornaments be neglected and deſpiſed. When the Church of Rome began to abound in wealth and authority, to have pluralities to maintaine their dignities, to leaue poore hirelings in their cures, to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ſoundneſſe in doctrine, knowledge, and the like graces; that they might ſeeme no leſſe religious; they began in ſtead thereof to be exerciſed in new manners of devotion,<note place="margin">See Pleſſis myſt. of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſ 24.</note> looking out of relickes, traditions, and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, to erect ſtately Temples, Organs, and Altars, to guild and adorne them with images of Saints, to have golden Chalices, and wooden Prieſts; to multiply feaſts and holidayes, to invent new orders and formes of will-worſhip, to uſe all ſeverity in bodily worſhip, devout poſture, and demure cariage; and to make all men conformable in thoſe things, to ordaine a world of ſuperfluous conſtitutions. But how was God moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in all theſe, while they did eate out religion? For people being taken up in thoſe, his ordinances were the leſſe regarded: and while the ſtately Temples were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in Cities,<note place="margin">Rev. 12.</note> the Church was faine to flee into the wilderneſſe; while the beauty of the outward ſtones were maintained,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</note> the living ſtones were trodden under feet and deſpiſed; while lights were ſet up in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, people ſate in darkneſſe and ignorance; while tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions were obſerved, Gods word was the leſſe reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and in time could neither bee obeyed nor heard; while the tables and Prieſts were adorned, men of knowledge and other the beſt gifts were leaſt eſteemed, while dead images of Saints were ſet up in the Church, beautified and worſhipped, the true and living Saints, ſuch as the <hi>Waldenſes, Huſsites,</hi> and <hi>Calveniſts</hi> were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted and martyred, and the very faith it ſelfe called hereſie.</p>
            <p>Looke now a little upon the Church of England, ſee
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:11723:49"/> how they abandon the cauſe of religion abroad and at home, deſpiſe and perſecute ſuch as ſeeke that the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God may be reſtored, Elders received, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, Arminianiſme, pluralities and non-reſidency ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, the true faith preached and maintained in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and Lectures, knowledge, faith, zeale, and other graces, nouriſhed and increaſed; and in the meane ſeem no leſſe religious, fall to building Temples, Organs, Tables, Altars, to ſatiate, if it were poſſible, the Clergy with titles of honour, juriſdictions, veſtments, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues and riches: and becauſe a Biſhop precedes a Baron, to thinke that nothing is too much to maintaine his ſtate, that is not too much for a Baron: and ſo for Deanes and Doctors, according to their degrees and places, which are the nurſeries of pluralities and non-reſidency. To call for obſervation of ceremonies, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, faſts, holidayes, externall geſture and devotion, and whatſoever elſe is commanded or practiſed in their conſtitutions and cuſtomes: wherein though they doe not yet abound ſo much as the Papiſts, yet it is the only religion in credit and faſhion; and as if Chriſt had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Biſhops to looke to nothing elſe, it doth and will eate out true religion and ſincerity. Howſoever, while Prelates and others, having pluralities to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their dignities, and leaving poore hirelings to ſerve their cures, thoſe better ornaments are neglected and perſecuted: are not theſe tokens that God is moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by them?</p>
            <p>I know well it is moſt irkſome to Prelates to heare of theſe things: they thinke no man ſhould dare to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt them, and eſpecially that the Elderſhip ought to be reſtored, according to Gods ordinance. They live as if they ſhunned no other plague, nor feared any other purgatory then a reformation. This fils their ſoules with
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:11723:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> Fiery indignation, and makes them, to be redeemed from it, breake out into threats, inquiſitions, and perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they may overcome their tormentors by cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, impriſonments, exemplary puniſhments, fines, and torments. Howſoever, if they can but by flatteries, invectives, whiſperings, and other ſhifts, keep the King and Councell ſo ignorant and blinde in thoſe things, that they may remaine firme on their ſide, they care for no more. But may not a man proteſt as plainly for God and his Church, as the French Ambaſſador did for the priviledges of France and the French Churches, in the Councell of Trent: that proteſtation angred the Prelates, but he defended it, ſaying, That <hi>thoſe were ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. of. the. Councel. Pag. 771. &amp;. 774.</note> 
               <hi>who having ſeene nothing but the Decretals, lawes of</hi> 400. <hi>yeares, did thinke that there were no Eccleſiaſticall lawes before them, that if any would reforme the King by the Decretals, he would reforme them by the decrees, and leade them alſo to more ancient times, not onely of S. Auſten, but of the Apoſtles alſo.</hi> Wherein the King juſtified him.</p>
            <p>Now as the hierarchy and ceremonies make not for the true ſervice of God, but ſerve to eate it out by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, as the Romiſh did, ſo neither doe they make for the ſervice of the King and State, but are againſt it, and very pernicious for every Nobleman and Ruler, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, 1. Becauſe while they are by them kept from the knowledge of Gods truth in matter of the Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, againſt Arminian errours, or any thing elſe the Biſhops would not have them know, that muſt needs be true in them, which our Saviour ſaith, <hi>He that wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in darkneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 12.35.</note> 
               <hi>knoweth not whither he goeth:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their deliberations in matters of preſerving the Church and State (which in theſe times are ſo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixed, by reaſon of popiſh practices, that commonly the cauſe and good of the one belongeth to the other)
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:11723:50"/> muſt needs bee accordingly canried, that is, with much blindneſſe and danger.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe if any King or great Favourite like the Duke, be in this error of the Hierarchy, Arminianiſme, or any other, the having of theſe great places in the Hierarchy in his gift, makes almoſt all the Clergy, and eſpecially the Prelates and Vniverſities to bee at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, to temporize, temper, forme and keepe bad di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity to their minde, by ſuch power and policy, that all the moſt skilfull Divines in the kingdome, ſhall not dare, or at leaſt not be able to helpe it; but whatſoever become of the truth, or reforming errours and abuſes, the honour of the Prelates and their abettors, muſt bee ſaved, as in the Court of Rome: and by theſe things they are prepared to rule a Synod, if occaſion ſerve, as the Court of Rome did that of Trent; and in the mean ſo to keepe divers errours and abuſes from the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their King, and to guard his eares from all juſt counſailes and complaints made againſt them or their confederates, or to pervert their drift by pretending his prerogative and government are taxed or queſtioned, and the Epiſcopall government eſtabliſhed by his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, is ſleighted and contemned, that nothing can bee heard, fearfull diviſions are made, Parliaments are for their ſakes diſſolved, the beſt counſels rejected, refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation hindred, notorious delinquents, Papiſts and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians emboldned, men in the greateſt truſt may dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be in the fellowſhip of Ieſuited Papiſts; what ever they practiſe, it is found in vaine to accuſe them: and by this meanes the King is either the laſt that knowes the truth and right in divers cauſes, or one that never comes to underſtand it, nor indeed to be willing to heare of it. Which is far from the wiſedome and diligence of the Pope and popiſh Princes, that ſeeke to ſupplant him and all true religion.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:11723:51"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Trent pag. 693.</note>Pius the 4. doubting that ſome Prelates and other great ones favoured the <hi>Protestants, reſolved to diſcover them, and was wont to ſay, that he was more wronged by the maſqued heretickes,</hi> then by the bare faced. Men, that love theire King and Religion, ſay as much of the maſqued Papiſts in England, and that therefore the Prelates and others vainly brag of the long peace and proſperitie England hath enjoyed, while other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries have ſmarted, when it hath beene procured by ſuch meanes; and more vainely thinke that God is well pleaſed with them, ſeing they haue no changes, but he hath ſuffered them to prevaile againſt ſuch as ſought the redreſſe, when they ſhould rather know that the long ſuffering of God leadeth to repentance, that all theſe things as they doe more and more diſable the king and his people from defending themſelues in the time of war, becauſe the Popiſh and Arminian factions are by them increaſed and God provoked; ſo without amendment, they will cauſe God to ſend a ſword amongſt them to auenge the quarrell of his covenant, when, thus weakned, they ſhalbe leſſe able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it. Some foiles they haue had, and their preſent ſecuritie is an ill <hi>omen</hi> of worſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe by theſe meanes Courtiers being nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in ſpirituall ignorance, Popiſt Princes that either labour to bring all to one Monarchie, or neerer &amp; neerer to Romiſh Religion, finde fit inſtruments in court and Councell to negotiate withall, to get leauges, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and articles of peace or war to theire beſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, to make diviſions, factions to corrupt and be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted; that is either for reward, or conſcience, to helpe Romiſh Religion vnder pretences of State policie, or being againſt the puritans: wherein they could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make things ſeeme to ſtand with religion without
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:11723:51"/> the conſent and confederacie of the Prelates. For if there were no hierarchie, no Prelates to countenance them, but the land were indeed of the reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, all would be aſhamed of ſuch counſailes as ſtand not with the good thereof: and Ieſuits could not find the meanes they doe, to be ſtickling by theire diſguiſed freinds, to trouble the ſtate, and by degrees and colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable pretences to alter Religion; wherein if Princes and favourits come to be corrupted, none ſo likely or pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to get things decreed to theire mindes, in Sinods, as Biſhops, that are thoſen by them and depend on them, as others on the Pope, the Trent fathers ſhewed it in many particulars.</p>
            <p>All which is as ill for the ſoules of thoſe Princes and ſtateſmen, as for the Church and State, what a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble caſe is it that Kings and Princes, who of all ſhould loue Chriſte and tender the good of his Church and people, as being nurſing fathers, will not take theſe things into conſideration, nor ſuffer the words of exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation? and that ſuch as are neere them will not vſe the meanes that they may know them? Miniſters, dare not touch vpon it, ſeing the Prelates flatter and are able to vndoe them wherein Romiſh Princes and Religion haue infinite aduantages againſt them. The meaneſt Ieſuits and Capuchins are admitted into the cloſets of Kings and Sates men, and permitted to convince or reprove in the cauſe of theire Religion, to exhort and animate them to conſtancie, vigilancie and courage, to vnmaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que and deſtroy the ſecret and open enemies thereof. When the Queene Regent of France had ſuffered <hi>Beza</hi> to ſpeake in Colloquie, a bold Ieſuit reproched the Proteſtants and openly reprehended the Queene <hi>for medling in matters</hi> that he ſaid <hi>belonged not to her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 454.</note> 
               <hi>but to the Pope</hi> &amp;c. yet was he not moleſted for it. They ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:11723:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> others, puniſh zealous ſpirits. Papiſts and other children of this world are wiſer in their generation then the children of light; more zealous, more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, (as is daily ſeene in France, Spaine, and all popiſh countries) which is ill for the State and Church of England. This therefore may be ſufficient to excuſe me for making this manifeſtation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe if there be not a reformation. God for all theſe evils is forced to plague ſuch a Church and State in many things, eſpecially in thoſe ſpirituall plagues. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.14. and 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.11.</p>
            <p>It is pretended, that they that ſeeke reformation of the Church, make ſchiſme. The Church of Rome ſaid as much for her ſelfe againſt them that ſought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme her in the time of <hi>Luther.</hi> And indeed the ſchiſm is rather made by the Biſhops and their ſupporters from the reformed Churches, and ſuch as hold Gods truth with them: which hath made the enemies attempt ſo much againſt them, and prevaile therein, while they ſaw the Engliſh to divided from them, and opoſite to them in theſe things, that they know the Biſhops and their ſupporters could not heartily favour them, and therefore would never get any effectuall ſupplies for them, but rather flatter and juſtifie ſuch friends, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hand betrayed them. So dangerous hath this divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion beene, and to is like to continue till the Elderſhip be reſtored, and there bee amongſt Proteſtants more unity in government and ceremonies.</p>
            <p>They reply, this is <hi>Cham</hi> like, to diſcover the naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ones father or mother, that the men of <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhemeſh</hi> were ſmitten for prying into the Arke, and <hi>Vz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zah</hi> for putting forth his hand to ſupport it: that ſo men meddle with things out of their element, that it belongs to privy Councellors and Biſhops to locke to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:11723:52"/> theſe things; which were the flattering arguments uſed to ſtop mens mouthes while the Palatinate and Rochel were in moſt danger, by the remiſſeneſſe and ſuſpected trechery of ſome diſguiſed Courtiers: now all is loſt, they muſt give us leave to ſay theſe places were not wel alledged then, much leſſe now to hinder reformation: that the hierarchy is not the Arke, nor any thing like it: that the Church of Rome hath ever uſed the ſame and like arguments to cover her filthineſſe.</p>
            <p>But ſay they, where got you this knowledge? if in the Engliſh Church, why doe you uſe it againſt her your mother? Doe you thinke the Church of Rome might not as juſtly ſay the like againſt <hi>Iohn Huſſe, Luther,</hi> and others before them? The truth is, there is but little of it in England, the Biſhops are ſo vigilant to ſuppreſſe it, and in ſtead thereof to cry for prayer, devotion and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Church: this is not to ſay, ignorance is the mother of devotion: but to approach toward it.</p>
            <p>To conclude, it is objected, that if we once goe about to alter any thing, we ſhall ever bee ſubject to change; men will ever be mad on reforming, more and more, till all be brought to Anabaptiſme, or at leaſt to Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme. O God what poore ſhifts doth the devill find to keepe men in evill? For this is as if one ſhould ſay, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer not to convert or reformed Papiſt, a drunkard, or a harlot, leſt the firſt turne Puritan, and then Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt; or take heed you returne not into the right way, becauſe it is narrow, and you may ſoone be turned into by paths on the other hand. Wherein they follow the policy of the Church of Rome. For when <hi>Luther</hi> had begun to dicover ſome errours, Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> 6. a Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man borne, being called out of Spaine the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, hoping to reduce all by a reformation, gave com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to his Nuncio the Biſhop of <hi>Fabriano,</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:11723:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> knowledge ingenuouſly,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Trent pag. 25.</note> 
               <hi>that this confuſion was cauſed by the ſinnes of men, eſpecially of the Prieſts and Prelates; confeſsing that ſome yeares ſince, ſome abominations have beene committed even in the holy Sea; many abuſes in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things</hi> &amp;c. Promiſſing <hi>to vſe all diligence that the Court of Rome, from whence Peradventure all this miſcheife proceeded ſhould be reformed firſt of all.</hi> And he ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to doe it, but was diverted by the Cardinall of <hi>Preneſte,</hi> who told him there was no hope to confound &amp; roote out the Lutherans, by correcting the manners of the Court, but rather that it would be a meanes to augment theire credit much more. <hi>For the people who alwaies judge by the events, when they ſhalbe aſſured by the following amendment, that the Popes government was iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reprehended, will perſwade themſelues likwiſe, that the other innouations propoſed have good foundation, and the Arch heretiques, ſeeing they haue overcome in one part, will not ceaſe to reprehend the rest. That reading the stories past, of</hi> the times when hereſies hare beene rayſed againſt the authoritie of the Church of Rome, it will appeare, that all took pretence from the corrupted manners of the Court. Neuertheleſſe never any Pope thought fit to reforme them, but after admonitions and inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vſed to induce the Princes to protect the Church. That whatſoever hath ſucceeded well here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore ought alwaies to bee obſerved and kept. That nothing did more ruine a government then to change the manner of ruling it. That no man hath ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed hereſies by reformations, cruſadoes, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing Princes and people to roote them out (that is with fire and ſword) which he ſhewed in the examples of Innocent III. and other Popes againſt the <hi>Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſes, Waldenſes</hi> and others. The Pope that was ſcarce warme in the Chaire, relating theſe things to his
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:11723:53"/> truſtie freinds <hi>William Encourt,</hi> and <hi>Theoderick Hezius</hi> ſaid the condition of Popes was miſerable, ſeeing it was plaine they could not doe good, &amp;c. yet he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to maintaine his promiſſes, thoughe it were to deveſt himſelf of all temporall dominion. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly ſent his <hi>Nuntio</hi> aboue mentioned to the diel of <hi>Noremberg,</hi> where he confeſſed the abuſes and promiſed the reformation, which the Pope liued not to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme.</p>
            <p>Clement the 7. that ſucceeded (and others after him) followed an other courſe: For when the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> V. to ſatisfie the Germans deſired that a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell might be called, the Pope anſwered,<note place="margin">Pag. 50.</note> that it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that the multitude was deceived, but to give it ſatisfaction in the demaund of a Councell, was not to give it more light, but to bring in popular licence. If it were granted them to make queſtion or ſeeke greater perſpicuitie in religion, they would immediatly alſo pretend to give laws for goverment, and to reſtraine the authoritie of Princes by decrees, &amp;c. For the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Grandies, he might aſſure himſelf, theire end was not pietie, but the making of themſelves Lords of the Eccleſiaſticall goods, and being become abſolute, to acknowledge the Emperour little or nothing, marke their cunning. But when the French Embaſſador had made requeſt for granting the cup to the laicks, with reaſon that it would keepe them in the Romiſh faith and from prying into other matters laid againſt the Church of Rome.<note place="margin">Pag. 459.</note> Pope Pius the IV. ſuddenly anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that he had ever thought that the communion of both kinds and mariage of preiſts were <hi>de jure poſitive:</hi> and therefore was thought to be a Lutheran in the laſt conclave. That the Emperour had made the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt for his ſonne demaunding the like for his people,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:11723:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> but that the Cardinals would never yeild unto it. Yet he promiſſed to ſpeake thereof in the next congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Where the Cardinall Rodolpho Pio de Carpi ſaid, that it was manifeſt, that this would not bee the laſt Demand of the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chmen in matter of religion, but a ſtep to propoſe an other, that afterward they will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the mariage of Preiſts, the vulgar toung in the miniſtrie of the Sacraments: which will have the ſame ground, becauſe they are <hi>de jure poſitivo,</hi> and muſt be-granted for the preſervation of many, which for poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike reaſons then alleadged might not be granted. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this there had beene much crie for reformation. Paul 3. cauſed divers Cardinals and others to aſſemble,<note place="margin">Pag. 85.</note> &amp; conſider of the errours for redreſſe. The Prelates made the Collection in writing, the Pope propoſed it in the Conſiſtorie. But Nicholas Scomberg a Dominican and a Cardinal oppoſed the reformation, ſaying. <hi>It would give occaſion to the Lutherans, to brag they had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced the Pope to make that reformation; and above all it would be a beginning to take away, not only the abuſes, but the good uſes alſo, and to endanger the whole ſtate of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. For by the reformation it would be confeſſed that the things provided againſt were deſervedly reprehended by the Lutherans, which would be a great abetting to theire whole Doctrine.</hi> In the councell, after celebrated, divers things were found amiſſe.<note place="margin">Seſſ. 22. Can. 9.</note> The Biſhops and Fathers of the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell made a decree for a reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but little could be obtained, much was ſhufled of, becauſe it could not be effected, but the authoritie and practiſe of the Pope and Cardinals muſt be queſtioned and reformed, if not overthrowen.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid of the Reformation of the Church of England, many things have beene propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, in Bookes and Parliaments, but little or nothing
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:11723:54"/> can be heard or reformed, leaſt a gap ſhould be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whereby the authoritie &amp; practiſe of the Biſhops ſhould be queſtioned and overthrowen, and if any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops be better inclined to reformation then others, they ſhalbe ſure to be hindred by the reſt, as theſe Popes were by the Cardinals, and with like reaſons. For Engliſh Biſhops, in like wiſdom, will not be knowen of any errour in the hierarchie, canons, traditions, ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies and government, but maintaine all, leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsing ſomewhat amiſſe, they ſhould looſe all, and be reduced to the government of other reformed chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            <p>There was a fault that hindred the Church of Rome from yeilding to reformation.<note place="margin">Caſſander conſult. 56. and 57.</note> And the fault (ſaith <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander</hi> a learned Papiſt) <hi>is to be laid upon thoſe which being puft up with vaine inſolent conceits of theire Eccleſiasticall power, proudely and ſcornfully contemned and rejected them which did rightly and modestly admoniſh the reformation. That the Church can never hope for any firme peace, unles they begin to make it, which have given cauſe of that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straction That this cannot be effected vnleſſe thoſe that are in place of Eccleſiastical government, would be content to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſomthing of their too much rigour, and yeild ſomwhat to the peace of the Church; and hearken to the earnest prayers and admonitions of godly men, will ſet themſelves to correct manifest abuſes, according to the rule of the divine Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and the primitive Church from which they have ſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi> (He might have ſaid, till the Kings hate the whore, make her deſolate, naked and burne her with fire) Shall I ſay this may alſo be ſaid of Engliſh Biſhops in caſe of theire hierarchie and traditions? I may add this to it, that God can never be pleaſed, nor the Church and State of great Britaine enjoy true happines, till the Prelates caſt their crownes at the feet of the <hi>Lord Ieſus;</hi>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:11723:55"/> or rather becauſe men diſpaire of that, till they be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them, and they ſubjected to the ordinances of God,<note place="margin">Rev. 5.6.</note> leaſt otherwiſe Chriſt, that hath the Elders a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his throne, and is in the midſt of them, ſay in his wrath,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.27.</note> 
               <hi>Thoſe mine enemies that would not that I ſhould raigne over them, bring hither,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>When reformation is deſired ſome flattering prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,<note place="margin">Canti. 8.4. Chap. 1.</note> to make men deſiſt, put it off with preaching on thoſe paſſages and the like. <hi>I charge you o daughters of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ye ſtir not up nor awake my love vntill he pleaſe, I am black but comly,</hi> &amp;c. The church hath ſpots, but they ſhould not be mentioned. <hi>Pray for the peace for Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, they ſhall proſper that love it,</hi> which if they of the Church of Rome had not in like manner a buſed, they could not have proceeded ſo far in errour, as they did: and yet they might as well alleadge theſe plates and the like to prove that prelates ought to procede Earles and Barons, to have pallaces and coaches, as to hinder and reprove men that ſeeke a due reformation.</p>
            <p>Others would have the people beleeve in this point, as the Church beleeveth, to relie on the underſtanding and judgment of the preiſts and prelates, like the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,<note place="margin">Mal. 2.7.</note> alleadging that place. <hi>The preists lips ſhould keepe knowledge, and they ſhould ſeeke the law at his mouth.</hi> which doth as well ſerve the papiſts,<note place="margin">Buckler of faith.</note> as them in this point: For, as maiſter <hi>Moulin</hi> obſerveth this is not a promiſſe but a commaundement. ſhewing preiſts their dutie, which they had not obſerved, as the following words mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt; <hi>But ye are departed out of the way: ye have cauſed men to ſtumble:</hi> which is as true, in this point, of the Prelates and others in England, as of the Papiſts in the ſame point and in others. We are therefore to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that rule,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>Beleeve not every Spirit but trie the Spirits,</hi> God gives ſuch knowledge to whom he pleaſeth; <hi>the wind bloweth where it liſteth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:11723:55"/>
            <p>They may perhaps find ſome other arguments to prove that the hierarchie, traditions and ceremonies ſhould be upheld, but none fairely deducted from the holy Scriptures, but rather grounded on humane po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie: which therefore are not worth the anſwering. For wee know likewiſe the papiſts preſſe many faire-ſeeming reaſons, for the Popes ſupremacie, and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in Peters chaire, merits, praying to Saints, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding mariage to Preiſts and other points of poperie. To which it is anſwer enough to prove that thoſe reaſons fight againſt the word and ordinance of God: and ſo doe theirs that pleade for the Engliſh hierarchie and tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as is already proved. Men therefore ſhould not be caried away with them, nor with an opinion of their learning and multitude that preach them; but rather thinke, Surely their kingdom is of this world: It makes so many that fight for it, becauſe there are in it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places of profit honour and authoritie to reward them, like as in the Romiſh Church; that if Chriſts kingdome were of this world he ſhould have as many for him: that to bee well informed in theſe points, it is no aſking of them who are intereſſed and partiall in the cauſe, but to remember what God ſaith,<note place="margin">Iſa. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Should not a people ſeeke unto theire God? To the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w and to the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie: if they ſpeake not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi> Which in theſe points, may be ſaid of 100 many, to theire great ſhame; becauſe it ſo muth concerneth the faith, and all the faithfull to have them well knowne, as is proved above, leaſt by the power and great names of the Biſhops, the faith come to be corrupted, the name of the Church, and the holy Ghoſt, uſurped and abuſed, as they have beene in divers Synods of Biſhops to the deſtruction of many ſoules.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:11723:56"/>
            <p>Let us therefore pray earneſtly and unceſſantly to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God the giver of all grace to purge the Church of England and the members thereof, that they with the reformed Churches may be <hi>like minded,</hi> in ſeeking the kingdom of God and the righteouſnes thereof, And ſeeing queſtionles that God hath many of his deare and elect people there, that are only blind in ſome few things, let us beg of God, that they may now ſee the things that <hi>belong to their peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1 9. Heb. 10.23. 1 Theſ. 5.24. Iſa. 25.6.</note> leaſt after they ſhould be <hi>hid</hi> from theire <hi>eyes.</hi> And let us aſke with confidence, that <hi>he is faithfull that hath promiſed, who will alſo doe it. For it is ſaid. In this mountaine ſhall the Lord of hoſts make unto all people a feaſt of fat things, a feast of wine on the lees, of fat things full of marrow, of wine on the lees well refined.</hi> Seeing therefore his ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are corrupted with mens inventions, wee may preſſe him with this promiſe that he will give us wine fined and purified, even his pureſt ordinances; as alſo with that which followeth,<note place="margin">verſ. 7.</note> 
               <hi>And he will deſtroy in this mountayne, the face of the covering cast over all people, and the vaile that is ſpread over all nations.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 30.21.</note> 
               <hi>And thine eare ſhall heare a word behind thee, ſayinge, This is the way, walke yein it when ye turne to the right hand, and when ye turne to the left.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though wee feare Satan will hinder it what he can,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.20.</note> let us beleeve that promiſe. The God of peace ſhall ſhortly bruiſe Satan under your feet. Neither thinke this impoſsible becauſe yet not only the Prelates, but divers religious Miniſters have neglected this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and reaſoned againſt it, ſo that there is great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference about theſe things, for God hath ſaid. I will give them one hart and one way.<note place="margin">Ier. 32, 39.</note> I will give you pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors according to mine hart which ſhall feed you with knowledge and underſtanding.<note place="margin">Cha. 3.15.</note> Neither be diſmaied
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:11723:56"/> becauſe as yet thoſe that have laboured moſt in this behalfe have beene forced into corners, and to live like Baniſhed men in murh ſorrow, for wee have this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.<note place="margin">Iſa. 35.10.</note> The ranſomed of the Lord ſhall returne and come to Sion with ſongs, and everlaſting ioy ſhalbe upon their heads. Neither ſay how ſhall this be, ſeing as yet ſo many greedie and corrupt ſhepheards are over us? For thus faith the Lord God. Behold I am againſt the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards and will require my flock at theire hand, and cauſe them to ceaſſe from feeding the flock, neither ſhall the Shepheards feed themſelvs any more: For I will deliver my flock from their mouth that they may not be meate for them. Acquaint thy ſelf with theſe and the like promiſes, and beleeve that he ſits at the right hand of God to intercede for the performance, who ſaith, whatſoever ye ſhall aſke in my name,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.13.</note> that will I doe, that the Father may be glorified in the ſonne. And if wee beleeve not, yet he abideth faithfull,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.13.</note> he cannot denie himſelf. To him therefore with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the holy Ghoſt, three perſons and one God, be rendred as due is, all power, might, majeſtie and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion now and for ever. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
